<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The poore vicars plea Declaring, that a competencie of meanes is due to them out of the tithes of their seuerall parishes, notwithstanding the impropriations. Written by Thomas Ryves Dr. of the Ciuile Lawes.</title>
            <author>Ryves, Thomas, Sir, 1583?-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851518</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851518</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1186:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poore vicars plea Declaring, that a competencie of meanes is due to them out of the tithes of their seuerall parishes, notwithstanding the impropriations. Written by Thomas Ryves Dr. of the Ciuile Lawes.</title>
                  <author>Ryves, Thomas, Sir, 1583?-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 152 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. M.DC.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" in a woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The poore vicars plea for tithes.</note>
                  <note>With "Sit laus Deo" on last page. Variant: lacking these words.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Ireland --  Finance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16794:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:16794:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:16794:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:16794:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE POORE VICARS PLEA.</p>
            <p>Declaring, that a competencie of <hi>meanes is due to them out of the</hi> Tithes of their ſeuerall Pariſhes, notwithſtanding the Impropriations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> THOMAS RYVES D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of <hi>the Ciuile Lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ad tenuitatem Beneficiorum neceſſariò ſequitur ignorantia Sacerdotum.</hi> Panormit.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by IOHN BILL. AN. DOM. M. DC. XX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16794:3"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two lions holding up a crown surmounted shield of the coat of arms of the United Kingdom above plaque</figDesc>
                  <head>DIEV ET MON DROIT.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16794:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO HIS SACRED</hi> MAIESTIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Religious and Gracious Souereigne, As it is not vnknowen to the world, in how miſerable a plight our poore Church of <hi>IRELAND</hi> ſtandeth at this preſent; So wee of that Kingdome know right well, and with all thankefulneſſe acknowledge, that your Maiestie hath euer made it one of your moſt Princely and Christian cares, to raiſe her vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb facs="tcp:16794:4"/>
if by any meanes you could, out of the dust, and to ſet her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Daughters, as ſometimes you did her Siſter of <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> which formerly lay buried vnder the like heape of <hi>Impropriations,</hi> as the other doeth at this preſent time.</p>
            <p>The knowledge whereof, dread Souereigne, hath emboldened mee, the meaneſt of all the Profeſſours of the Lawes, to preſent this ſhort Diſcourſe vnto your Highneſſe: wherein I haue endeauoured to prooue, that the poore Miniſters of that Church, ought to be more competently prouided for, then now they are, and that, out of the Tithes belonging to their ſeuerall
<pb facs="tcp:16794:4"/>
Churches, not by Praerogatiue, whereof your Maieſtie is euer ſparefull, but by a due courſe of Law, alreadie there establiſhed: Wiſhing from my heart, that this cauſe of GOD and of his Church, had found an Aduocate, anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the dignitie and iustice of it. As it is, I ſhall humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your Maieſtie, that neither the unworthineſſe of my perſon, neither yet the vnlikelihood of the matter, be any preiudice to the worth and trueth of the cauſe it ſelfe; but rather, that your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will vouchſafe to looke downe upon this poore endeavour of your humble Seruant, with a fauourable eye, and to ſupply thoſe manifold
<pb facs="tcp:16794:5"/>
defects, which may happily bee found in the handling of ſo great and difficult a cauſe, out of that abundant and incomparable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Learning and Wiſedome, which GOD hath ſo richly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed your Princely minde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: In hope whereof, with my humble prayers to Almightie GOD, for the preſeruation of your Maieſties long and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Reigne, I rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe moſt loyall Subiect and humble ſeruant, THO. RYVES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16794:5"/>
            <head>THE POORE VICARS PLEA <hi>for Tithes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He proſperous and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie peace which this poore Kingdome of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath of late yeeres inioyed, is ſuch, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Fathers euer ſaw, nor can bee ſampled out of any Records or Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of former ages. The plough now walketh without feare, the wayfaring man trauaileth without danger, the lawes are executed in euery place alike. <hi>Cocherings</hi> are reduced to <hi>Chiefe-rents;</hi> The poore Tenant beginneth to ſtand for his right againſt his tyrannizing and cutting Landlord: The name of a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16794:6"/>
               <hi>Kerne</hi> is almoſt forgotten. The woods and faſtnes are left for beaſts. The men are drawen to Villages and Townes, and all reduced (thanked bee God) to a meaſure of good ciuility.</p>
            <p>Onely the Church in this common ioy mourneth, looking pale and wan, as if ſhe had been either newly taken out of a burning feuer, or came lately flying out of a bloody battell. The Churches in moſt places lie waſte: and where Churches are, there want, rather Miniſters able to inſtruct the people, then people capable of inſtruction. So that, if his Maieſtie ſhould bee pleaſed to caſt his eye vpon the Temporall and Eccleſiaſticall eſtate of this his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome both at once, he might well ſigh in himſelfe, and ſay as ſometime King <hi>Dauid</hi> did, <hi>Ecce Ego nunc habito in domo cedrina,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Lib. Chronic. c. 17 v. 1.</note> 
               <hi>dum arca foederis ſub aulaeis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is the cauſe of this her po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, and extreme calamitie hard to be diſcerned: would God the remedie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16794:6"/>
were as eaſie to bee found. The ſole cauſe therefore of this her miſerie, is the multitude of <hi>Benefices,</hi> long ſince taken from the dayly Miniſters of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and conuerted to other vſes: But principally and in greaeſt number ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the luxury of the Monks. For there was an age when <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> ſeemed to conſiſt onely in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> and in beſtowing large reuenues vpon them when they were built. But thoſe <hi>Monkeries,</hi> as they were from the beginning excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding burdenſome to the Temporall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of all kingdomes in which they were erected, ſo in ſhort time they grew banefull to the Churches, by reaſon of the multitude of Church liuings which they procured dayly to bee appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their vſes: wherupon it was, that (among other grieuances) which the <hi>Chriſtian Nations</hi> complained of in the Councell of <hi>Constance,</hi> &amp; whereof they required reformation; this was one,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16794:7"/>
That the number of <hi>Vnions</hi> and <hi>Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations;</hi> that is to ſay, of <hi>Appropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> was ouer much increaſed in all king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. And the <hi>Councell</hi> thereupon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That all ſuch <hi>Appropriations</hi> as had bin in certain yeeres before ſhould be reuerſed; Yet with this reſeruation, <hi>viz. Vnleſſe they were made vpon iuſt and lawfull cauſes:</hi> which was nothing elſe, but to blind the eyes of the world, and to ſend away the complainants, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent for the preſent. The <hi>Councell of Trent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Trident. Seſſ.</hi> 7.</note> alſo not long after reuoked all <hi>Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations</hi> which had been made in four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeeres before. But I could neuer finde that this <hi>Canon</hi> tooke effect any more then that other of <hi>Conſtance</hi> did. Sure I am, that the French writers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that they haue been as frequent in <hi>France</hi> ſince that <hi>Councill</hi> as before: and ſo frequent, that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſities,</hi> (which by a laudable cuſtome of that Realme haue a right of <hi>Nomination</hi> to a <note place="margin">Petr. Rebuffus Tracta. nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>num.</note> third part of the Benefices therein, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16794:7"/>
with the Secular <hi>Clergie,</hi> and <hi>Lay-Patrons,</hi> finding no meaſure in them, nor other remedie againſt them) vſe to appeale from them, as from abuſes, to the high Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> in that Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Neither haue theſe <hi>Monaſteries</hi> done more harme to the <hi>Church</hi> in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, then they haue by their example. For from them, <hi>Chantries, Colledges, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spitals,</hi> and <hi>Nunneries,</hi> learned to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure <hi>Appropriations</hi> to be made vnto them. By meanes whereof, the ſeuerall Pariſhes throughout <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in ſhort time to grow deſtitute of learned Teachers, and by this occaſion more then by any other, fell from ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to barbariſme, and from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of true Religion, to groſſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and meere ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>But of all Kingdomes of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world, I ſuppoſe that neuer any was ſo ſurcharged and ruined with this heauy burden as this poore Kingdome of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16794:8"/>
hath beene, and is. For the more barbarous the people was, the more were they addicted to ſuperſtition; and the more ſuperſtitious, the more eaſie to be wrought vpon in this kinde. To inſtance in one for all: I haue obſerued out of an olde <hi>Liger booke</hi> of the <hi>Abbey</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Regiſt. Sancti Thome in le Breminghams Tour Dublin.</note> of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> neere <hi>Dublin</hi> (a houſe of no very olde foundation) That in few yeeres after it was erected, it had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured fiftie nine <hi>Church liuings</hi> in part, or in whole, to be appropriated to their vſes. Neither may we doubt, but that <hi>Kilmainim,</hi> Saint <hi>Maries,</hi> and other ſuch houſes, which were in great number in and about <hi>Dublin,</hi> and other parts of that Kingdome, had their ſhare alike. By meanes whereof it is come to paſſe, that a man ſhall there finde few Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſerued by other then poore Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars and Stipendarie <hi>Curats,</hi> and thoſe, for the moſt part, men of ſuch courſe ſtuffe, as hardly can a man ſay, whether ſuch men bee leſſe worthy of better
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16794:8"/>
maintenance, or ſuch maintenance of better men.</p>
            <p>I haue beene told that Doctor <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston,</hi> a learned <hi>Ciuilian,</hi> and (not long ſince) a worthy Lo. <hi>Chancellour</hi> of this Kingdom, pitying the miſerable plight of this poore Church, deuiſed the meanes how to haue all thoſe <hi>Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations</hi> reſtored to their primer vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and that hee wrote a large <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> to that effect, which he intended to ſend to her Maieſtie of happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, but that death preuented him, and (he dying) that worke aborted with him. I muſt confeſſe, that the line of my vnderſtanding is too ſhort to reach to ſo deepe a point of learning: but well can I ſhew, what hath beene done heretofore in the like caſe, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Church; and how (without wrong to any man, and by a laudable due courſe of law) there may and ought to be a competent maintenance raiſed vnto euery Miniſter, out of the Tithes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16794:9"/>
belonging to his owne Church; and that by the immediate authoritie of the Biſhop, notwithſtanding the <hi>Appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> as now they ſtand, and ſo the poore eſtate of this Church be made a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deale more tolerable then now it is. And this is the <hi>Argument</hi> of this ſhort <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> enſuing: an Argument, which I know wil ſeeme harſh, and not ſound well in the eares of thoſe men who haue hitherto liued in the quiet poſſeſsion of the whole. But they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for the moſt part, men of honour and wiſedome, and ſuch as can eaſily appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, That if happily my loue vnto our Mother the <hi>Church,</hi> hath driuen me into an errour, my errour cannot hurt them: And if I ſhall maintaine a trueth, the trueth will defend both it ſelfe and me: In the one caſe they need not, in the other they ought not; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope and preſume, that in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour they will not be offended at mee. As for the <hi>Argument</hi> it ſelfe, it will in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16794:9"/>
my poore vnderſtanding bee made cleere and ſufficiently prooued to all men of indifferencie and wiſedome, if I ſhall be able to make it appeare. Firſt, that by the Lawes <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> which were in force before, and at the time of the diſſolution of <hi>Abbeys</hi> in the reigne of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. The <hi>Biſhops</hi> had full power and authoritie within their ſeuerall Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſes to allot, or cauſe to be allotted out of euery Benefice, ſo much of the Tithes as might well ſerue for a fit maintenance of the Miniſter, any Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation notwithſtanding. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That the ſame <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> ſtand hitherto in full force and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlled by any <hi>Statute</hi> of either Kingdome.</p>
            <p>To put hooke to corne therefore. And firſt to make it cleare, That by the courſe of the <hi>Canon Lawes,</hi> and by the practiſe vſed in thoſe daies, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops had ſuch power ouer the <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,</hi> and other ſuch like houſes, while
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16794:10"/>
they were in their cheefeſt Ruffe. It is to be obſerued, That it was the opinion which the world had conceiued of the pietie, charitie, and deuotion of <hi>Monks,</hi> that firſt cauſed thoſe ample reuenues, both Temporall and Eccleſiaſticall to be caſt vpon them. This opinion was the more confirmed in the minds of men by their laudable beginnings, for as the liberalitie of the rich to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, was very great; ſo were alſo their hoſpitality in receiuing ſtrangers, their charitie in redeeming captiues, their deuotion in releeuing the poore, and other Almeſdeeds no leſſe. As for theſe Benefices which were annexed to their houſes, and appropriated to their vſes, it is reported, that they vſed them, as if they vſed them not, and taking thereof a ſmall penſion for themſelues, they left the reſt to their <hi>Vicar,</hi> which performed the daily office in the <hi>Church.</hi> And no maruaile: for had they appeared in their owne likeneſſe at the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16794:10"/>
firſt, euery man had ſhut doores againſt them: But in proceſſe of time, as their Luxurie, cauſed by their idleneſſe, ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp their deuotion, ſo their Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, the naturall begotten daughter of their Luxurie, quenched the fire of their Charitie. Then began they to take the whole fruits of thoſe Benefices into their owne hands, and to thruſt the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> to his pittance, not regarding how vnworthy the man were, ſo he would content himſelfe with little wages. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelues, who vſe to winke at ſmall faults in their tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie ſeruants, grew offended at this their inſatiable auarice, fearing, and foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that in the end, it would turne to the diſcredit of the <hi>Papacie,</hi> whoſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they were, to the ruine of the Pariſh-Churches, and decay of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in all places where they came. The firſt which oppoſed himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, was <hi>Pope Alexander</hi> the third, about the yeere of our Lord God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16794:11"/>
1170. He wrote to the <hi>Monkes</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Regulars of the Church and Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of <hi>Yorke,</hi> a certaine <hi>Decretall,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hauing firſt blamed their couetous diſpoſition in this kind, he addeth theſe words. <hi>Intelleximus quod in Eccleſijs ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aritia. extra d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>de quibus certas Penſiones conſueuistis percipere, portiones &amp; antiquos reditus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraſtis, quos nonnulli Clerici Eccleſiarum ipſarum habuiſſe noſcuntur: Idcóque man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus, quatenus, fi quas portiones, velan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquos reditus Clericorum fine conſenſu Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopi veſtri minuere praeſumpſiſtis, ad integritatem priſtinam reuocetis.</hi> From whence that appeareth to bee true which was ſaid before: That in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning <hi>Monkes,</hi> and others were wont to reſerue to themſelues a penſion one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of thoſe Churches which they held appropriated to their vſes, leauing the groſſe of their Tithes which were the proper ancient reuenue of the Church, to the Vicars or other Curats <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> extra de pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd</note> of them. And ſo <hi>Panormitan</hi> vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16794:11"/>
this Decretall, and therefore ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it in this manner: <hi>Religioſi reditus Eccleſiarum ipſarum diminuere non poſſunt, reſpectu portionis quae debetur Rectoribus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Panormit. ib.</note> 
               <hi>ſeu vicarijs earundem;</hi> And a little after he ſaith, that the religious men could not increaſe their owne Penſion, <hi>Nec poſſunt diminuere portionem ſolitam dari Rectoribus earundem Eccleſiarum:</hi> Some men I know, &amp; among them <hi>Aufrerius</hi> a learned Canoniſt in his 109. Deciſion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aufrer. dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 109.</note> will haue it to be vnderſtood of the Couents of inferior Priories, rather then of the Vicars of Pariſh Churches, being led into this opinion, no doubt, by the word <hi>Clericorum;</hi> which yet, as <hi>Suidas</hi> and others teſtifie, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all ſorts of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> and all others which had taken vpon them any degree of holy Orders, were they Secular, or were they Regular, and doth more properly ſignifie a Miniſter of the Church, as one which is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly called <hi>in ſortem Domini,</hi> then it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16794:12"/>
doth a Monke or Friar.</p>
            <p>But of whomſoeuer it was meant, it ſeemeth that this Conſtitution ſerued only for a warning peece, and did but randon ouer the Monkes for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, without doing them any greater harme; for, <hi>vana eſt omnis constitutio quae contra facientibus poenam non imponit.</hi> And therefore as the diſeaſe increaſed, ſo was the remedie more and more inforced: wherefore the ſame <hi>Alexander,</hi> not long after, being duly informed of the ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour of our <hi>Monkes</hi> in this kind, and that contrary to the old cuſtome, they ſuffered the poore Curats to take al the paines, and not to pertake of the gaines in any reſonable ſort, wrote to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Worcester</hi> in this manner. <hi>De monachis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">c. de Monachis Extra de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend.</note> 
               <hi>qui vicarios Eccleſiarum parochia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ita grauant, vt hoſpitalitatem tenere non poſsint, eam prouidentiam habeas quod ad praeſentationem eorum nullum recipias, niſi tantum ei de prouentibus Eccleſiae coram refuerit aſsignatum, vnde iura Epiſcopalia</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16794:12"/>
               <hi>poſsint perſoluere, &amp; congruam ſuſtentatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the better vnderſtanding of which <hi>Conſtitution</hi> it is to be noted, that in all thoſe Churches which were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to any <hi>Monaſterie,</hi> the <hi>Monkes</hi> as they were to receiue the fruites to their owne vſes, ſo were they to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their Vicar to the Biſhop, by him to be canonically inſtituted to the cure of ſoules, and were alſo to allow ſo much out of the Tithes, as in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the Ordinarie might ſeeme enough to mainetaine the Vicar in a competent and a conuenient manner, his calling, degree, and quality conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as alſo to diſcharge Procurations, and other duties belonging to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, to mainetaine hoſpitality, and to ſupport and defray all other charges belonging to ſuch a Benefice, as ſhall hereafter more fully bee declared. But becauſe the <hi>Monkes</hi> would make them no other allowance then ſuch as is now
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16794:13"/>
commonly made to our hirelings heere in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Therefore the Pope willed the Biſhop (to whom the care of theſe things properly belonged) to reforme this abuſe, and not to admitte of any Clerke at their preſentation, vnleſſe the <hi>Monkes</hi> would firſt make an allowance of ſo much of the Tithes or other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits to the vſe of the Vicar, as would ſuffice for all the aboue named charges, ſo ſaith <hi>Panormitane, Innocentius, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buffus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Panormit. &amp; Innocen. ad</hi> D. 6 <hi>de Monar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chis Rebuff. de congr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> and other Writers, expoſitors of the <hi>Canon Law.</hi> For albeit there were not in thoſe daies any <hi>Vicarages</hi> endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (for this is a terme of our <hi>Common Lawes,</hi> and vnknowen vnto the <hi>Canons)</hi> yet was there euer a perpetuall Vicar to be reſident in the Pariſh, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by licence (as now is vſed) but by Canonicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution from the Ordinarie, at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the <hi>Monkes:</hi> vnto which inſtitution the Biſhop could not bee compelled, vnleſſe the <hi>Monkes</hi> had firſt ſet out a competent allowance for the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16794:13"/>
Vicar, as the Ordinary ſhould thinke meete. And this was then thought to be a ſufficient tie vpon the <hi>Monkes,</hi> to reſtraine their auarice, and to compell them to make a more liberall allowance for the Vicar: ſeeing that the cure of ſoules, which originally, or (as the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts</hi> ſpeake) habitually reſided in them, could not otherwiſe be ſupplied. And not long after the ſame <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſitting in the <hi>Laterane</hi> Councell, iſſued forth a <hi>Canon</hi> of the ſame nature with his Decretall, but in termes more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and in forme as followeth. <hi>Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pandae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">C. extirpandae extra de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>conſuetudinis vitium in quibuſdam partibus inoleuit, quod ſcilicet parochiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Eccleſiarum patroni, &amp; aliae quaedam perſonae prouentus ipſarum, ſibi penitus ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantes, Presbyteris earundem ſeruitijs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putatis relinquant adeo exiguam portionem quod ex eâ nequeant congruè ſuſtentari; nam (vt pro certo didicimus) in quibuſdam Regionibus parochiales Presbyteri, pro ſua ſustentatione non obtinent, niſi quartam</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16794:14"/>
               <hi>quartae: i. ſextam decimam decimarum. Cum igitur os bouis ligari non debeat tritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis; ſed qui altari ſeruit de altari viuere &amp; debeat. Statuimus vt conſuetudine qualibet Epiſcopi vel Patroni, vel cuiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet alterius non obſtante, portio Presbyteris ipſis ſufficiens aſsignetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Canon</hi> (as <hi>Panormitane</hi> in his <hi>Commentaries</hi> vpon the ſame ſaith) is <note place="margin">Panormitan. ib.</note> properly to bee vnderſtood of thoſe Churches, <hi>Quarum proprietas pertinet ad alium, i.</hi> The property whereof belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to another, then the Vicar or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the place; which may, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed muſt, be vnderſtood, either of <hi>Monaſteries</hi> to which they were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated, or of dignities to which they were annexed, or of laie perſons, to whom they were giuen to be held in fee, as they are now held by proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with vs, eſpecialy in <hi>France</hi> thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and in ſome parts of <hi>Germanie,</hi> where <hi>Charolus Martellus</hi> (as the <hi>French</hi> Hiſtories report, and no leſſe appeareth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16794:14"/>
out of the body of the <hi>Canon Law)</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that great and glorious battell neere <hi>Tours</hi> vpon the <hi>Loire,</hi> againſt the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins,</hi> wherein hee ſlew of the Infidels <note place="margin">De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> en ſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ectaire de France.</note> three hundred threeſcore and fifteene thouſand men, not hauing wherewith elſe to reward and content his Armie for that daies ſeruice, gaue all, or the greateſt part of the Tithes to them in fee for euer: yet in all theſe there was ſtill a Vicar to be maintained, and a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable allowance to bee made for his entertainement. But becauſe all theſe in their ſeuerall places tooke the whole reuenue of euery Benefice vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, not allotting to the Vicar aboue the ſixteenth part of the whole profits: by reaſon whereof ſundry miſchiefes grew vnto the Church: euery man pleading a cuſtome, and that they had long vſed to pay no more. Therefore the Pope (who according to the courſe of thoſe times, was reputed to haue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne authority in caſes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16794:15"/>
commanded all Biſhops to root out this euill practiſe, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any cuſtome belonging to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Biſhop, which held them peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vnited to his table, or Patron which had them in fee, or any other, as <hi>Monkes,</hi> to whoſe vſes they were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated, they ſhould reforme this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe in themſelues and others, within their ſeuerall iuriſdictions, and cauſe a larger proportion to bee made vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Prieſt or Vicar deputed to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Church.</p>
            <p>There was after this another Decree publiſhed by <hi>Clement</hi> the third, in theſe words. <hi>Sicut nobis tua fraternitas intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">C Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t extra de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Monachi quidam &amp; Canonici Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Eccleſias quae ad praeſentationem eorum pertinent proprijs vſibus deputare nituntur; nec volunt ad eas, cum vacauerint vocare perſonas, &amp;c. admiſſos ita penſionibus one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes, &amp;c. Nolentes autem, vt ſtatus Eccleſiae debitus &amp; antiquus per inſolentiam alicuius ſubuertatur. Mandamus quatenus</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16794:15"/>
               <hi>niſi a iuriſdictione tua exemptae ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t Eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> ſupradictae, praedictos exceſſus ſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eas rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onabiliter emendare: Et niſi praedictae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae infra tempus in Lateranenſi Concilio constitutum, ad vacantes Eccleſias tibi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonas idoneas preſentauerint, extunc tibi li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat, appellatione remota, in iiſdem ordinare Rectores qui eis praeeſſe nouerint &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Conſtitution</hi> ſuffereth ſome quarrell and diſpute vpon ſundry points. But for our preſent purpoſe, <note place="margin">Petrus Rebuff. tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. port.</note> 
               <hi>Petrus Rebuffus</hi> ſaith, that it iſſued foorth vpon this occaſion. <hi>Alexander</hi> the third (as hath beene ſaid) had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that a Biſhop ſhould not admitt of the Preſentee of the <hi>Monkes,</hi> vnleſſe they would firſt aſſigne a ſufficient por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the profits, for his maintenance: whereupon the <hi>Monkes</hi> would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent any Vicar at all, but either left their Churches vnſerued, or ſerued them with poore mercenary Curats, ſuch as we haue hundreds here in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16794:16"/>
ſo the Church was worſe ſerued, and the Church-men worſe prouided for, then before. Whereupon this <hi>Clement</hi> by this Conſtitution ordained, That in caſe they did not prouide ſufficient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons within the time limited in the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran Councill,</hi> which was of ſix months, Then the Biſhop ſhould collate by his owne authority, as in other caſes of laps and deuolution: Excepting alwaies thoſe <hi>Monkes,</hi> which by ſpeciall priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge were exempted from his Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for with theſe the <hi>Ordinary</hi> was not permitted, but rather forbidden to deale.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, about the yeare of our Lord 1240. perceiuing that the aboue mentioned Conſtitution of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, had taken ſome good effect with the ordinary ſort of <hi>Monkes:</hi> and taking notice: That the Exempt <hi>Monkes</hi> which were immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubiect to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> continued ſtill to oppreſſe their Vicars with intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16794:16"/>
exactions, and to make them ſuch ſmall allowances, that the poore men were not able to liue thereon, made a Decree, That the Conſtitution of <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſhould alſo take place and be of force againſt the Exempt <hi>Monkes:</hi> The words (after mention made of the Decree of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and of the great abuſes which grew by the auarice of the priuiledged <hi>Monkes)</hi> follow in this manner. <hi>Nos itaque volentes ſuper hoc</hi> 
               <note place="margin">c. Suſcepti. de praebend. in ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> 
               <hi>ſalubre remedium adhiberi, praeſenti Decreto ſtatuimus &amp; mandamus Constitutionem hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſmodi, quoad omnes patronos Eccleſiarum, religioſos, tam exemptos quam non exemptos &amp; alios, inuiolabiter obſeruari, conſuetudine contrariâ non obſtante.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all theſe <hi>Lawes,</hi> though groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon great reaſon were of little force to preuaile againſt a miſchiefe which had ſpread it ſelfe ſo farre, and rooted it ſelfe ſo deepe, by cuſtome, and the redreſſe whereof muſt pinch the belley of the <hi>Monke:</hi> For what effect
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16794:17"/>
could a bare <hi>Mandamus</hi> worke in a caſe of this nature, there being no penaltie inflicted vpon the offender.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non canis à corio facile absterrebitur vncto.</hi> The <hi>Templars</hi> (for they were thoſe which moſt offended in this kind, and which of all others were the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall occaſion of theſe Decrees) were too couetous to obey for conſcience, and too mightie to bee terrified with words. And for mine owne part I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee, what this was elſe, but either a feare to diſpleaſe them; or elſe a meere mockery of the world, to commaund this thing to be done, and yet neither to inflict a penaltie vpon the offender, nor giue authoritie to the Reformer. I confeſſe, that our Doctors and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> reckon this for one of the caſes wherein the <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> had power giuen him ouer the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledged <hi>Monkes:</hi> But neither were theſe ſuch men as would giue their beards for the waſhing, neither would the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16794:17"/>
venture vpon ſuch a point of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation without a more expreſſe warrant: ſeeing that Kings themſelues had their power in ſuſpect and iealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which alſo was in the end their bane and ouerthrow.</p>
            <p>At the laſt came <hi>Clement</hi> the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>t, a through man, in whatſoeuer he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke This Pope in the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enne</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> made a <hi>Canon</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of this abuſe, more abſolute then any of his predeceſſors had made before him: For, hauing repeated the Conſtitutions of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, and of <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, and finding them both to bee imperfect, he adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all Biſhops: <hi>Ne praeſentatum alique<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per quamcunque perſonam Eccleſiaſticam, ius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">C. Vt c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nst <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. de Iurepatr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Clemens.</note> 
               <hi>praeſentandi habentem, ad aliquam Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am admittant, niſi intra certum terminum competentem praeſent antibus per Dioceſanos ipſos praefigendum fuerit coram ijs congrua de prouentibus Eccleſiae por tio aſsignata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And knowing wel by the experience of times paſt, what little effect a bare
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16794:18"/>
command was like to take with this kinde of men. Hee further ordained, that in caſe the <hi>Monkes</hi> ſhould not make ſuch allowance as was fit for the vſes there expreſſed within ſuch reaſonable time as the Ordinary ſhould prefixe, <hi>Vt extunc Dioceſani debeant praeſentatum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>id.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; in poenam praeſentantium ad Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſanos ipſos potestas aſſignationis huiuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di deuoluatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which wordes both the Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee was ſecured in his poſſeſſion, as ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it by Collation from the Biſhop, and the right of aſſigning the <hi>Vicars</hi> portion taken from the <hi>Monkes,</hi> and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the Ordinary of the Dioceſſe: And moreouer, to arme him aſwel with power to execute, as with authoritie to command ouer the exempt and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged <hi>Monkes,</hi> In the end of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution hee addeth theſe wordes, <hi>Ad quae omnia integraliter adimplenda, nec non ad obſeruationem debitae aſsignationis per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>id.</note> 
               <hi>Dioceſanum faciendae Religioſos praedictos,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16794:18"/>
               <hi>&amp; alios quoſlibet à Dioceſanis ijſdem Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtica volumus cenſura compelli; non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantibus exemptionibus, aut alijs quibuſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet priuilegijs, conſuetudinibus vel ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quae circa praemiſſavel eorum aliquod Religioſis ipſis, aut alijs, in nullo volumus ſuffragari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this authoritie granted to the Ordinarie ouer the exempt <hi>Monkes,</hi> is yet more cleere by another conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame <hi>Clement,</hi> and in the ſame <hi>Councell,</hi> wherein becauſe <hi>Abbats</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regular <hi>Prelates</hi> were wont to hold their ſubordinate Priories and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches belonging to them, in their owne hands; or otherwiſe to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them with exactions, or happily not preſenting any at all to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> for inſtitution, therefore it was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that in caſe they preſented not within ſixe moneths. <hi>Dioceſani locorum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">C. Vnico de ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple. neglige Praelato. in Clement.</note> 
               <hi>in non exemptis ſua, in exemptis verò Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolica authoritate negligentiam ſuper hoc ſuppleant eorundem, Prioratus, Eccleſias, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrationes,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16794:19"/>
               <hi>&amp; Beneficia huiuſmodi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to the end the Ordinaries might haue power in themſelues, not onely to ſupplie their negligence, but alſo to reſtraine their auarice: Therefore it followeth in the ſame Decree in this manner. <hi>Eadem quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> authoritate Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſani ſuffulti, nullo modo permittant quòd ij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Praelati, Prioratus, Eccleſias, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrationes aut Beneficia applicent menſis ſuis, penſioné<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue nouas ijs imponant, aut veteres augeant, ſiue quae ipſis de nouo imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſitae ſiue auctae ſoluantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The difference betweene this and the former conſtitution is this. In the former, <hi>Biſhops</hi> had power to make or cauſe to be made a ſufficient allowance to the Incumbent, In the later, to ſee that the <hi>Monkes</hi> layd no new exactions, or impoſed greater penſions vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them: which difference aroſe from a diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of cuſtome vſed among the <hi>Monkes.</hi> For ſometimes (and that was the more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16794:19"/>
ancient and better faſhion) they left the groſſe of the tithes and other profits to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receiued by the Vicar, reſeruing to themſelues onely a penſion, to bee payed out of the whole by the Vicar, which afterwards they ſought immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to increaſe: and ſometime they ſet their owne Proctor to take vp the maine profits, and left onely a part or portion to the Vicar, which they ſought continually to diminiſh: But in both caſes the <hi>Biſhops Croſier</hi> had the priuiledged <hi>Monke</hi> by the legge, aſwell as hee had the other.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Clement</hi> made bolder with all ſorts of <hi>Monkes</hi> then any Pope did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after him. And as for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt Orders of them, whereas they were by vertue of their exemption im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly ſubiect to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> which could not from ſo farre off, looke well into their dealings, he made them in this and certaine other caſes liable to the Biſhops, of the ſeuerall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16794:20"/>
Dioceſſe; not as vnto Ordinaries, but as to <hi>Delegates</hi> from the See of <hi>Rome</hi> for perpetuitie, as heere appeareth. And laſtly ſubiected them wholly in this manner to the viſitation and rodde of correction of the Biſhops, with a <hi>Non obſtante</hi> of all their exemptions or other Prerogatiues and Priuiledges whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Templars,</hi> of whom I ſpake before, This alſo was that <hi>Clement,</hi> which, either fearing or enuying their <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ement. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> greatneſſe, by reaſon of their wealth, reputation in warres, alliance with great houſes, and populous fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which they had in euery corner of euery State and Kingdome, laide the traine to blow them vp in an inſtant; and combining with <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France</hi> and other <hi>Princes,</hi> cauſed them all to be ſurpriſed in a moment, and to be made away, ſome by maſſacre, and ſome by courſe of Law, laying to their charge <hi>Confederacie</hi> with the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> abnega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16794:20"/>
of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſecret rites, ſtrange luſts, and other crimes, whereof, ſome ſay, they were not guiltie. A <hi>Mirrour</hi> for the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> to beholde their greatneſſe, and to foreſee their ruine in. They are (as the Hiſtorian ſaith of Elephants) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Deca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>anceps Belluae genus,</hi> as likely to turne vpon him that vſeth them, as to runne vpon them againſt whom they are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, late King of the <hi>French,</hi> flattered them for feare, and could not thereby eſchew their plots. And it is not long ſince that <hi>La Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teliere</hi> the Kings Attourney generall in <hi>Paris,</hi> in the caſe betweene the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity <note place="margin">En ſon plai d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pour l' vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite contre le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ieſuites.</note> and them, deliuered in open Court, That they are ſo fortefied and cabled vp with the Graunts and Priuiledges of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 14. and other <hi>Popes,</hi> that now no gunne-ſhot or thunder of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication can make breach vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; That ſundry <hi>Popes</hi> of latter times haue ſought to bring them into ſome order, but haue not beene able to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16794:21"/>
preuaile. And laſtly, that <hi>Aquauiua</hi> their Generall had at that preſent no leſſe power and credit in <hi>Rome</hi> then the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe. The ſaying is old and true, <hi>Quem quiſque metuit periiſſe expetit;</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot long endure a fellow <hi>Pope</hi> in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to returne to our purpoſe. By that which hath beene ſaid, it may clearely appeare, That the Biſhop of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Dioceſſe, what as Ordinary, what as a legall and perpetuall delegate of the <hi>Pope,</hi> had full power in all caſes of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation, to compell the Abbat of what ſort, order, or priuiledge ſoeuer, to make a conuenient allowance out of the Tithes and other profits of euery Benefice, for the ſufficient and decent maintenance of the <hi>Curate</hi> ſo that had theſe Lawes beene as carefully put in vre, as they were in writing, the Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of the <hi>Monkes</hi> had beene reſtrained, and the <hi>Curats</hi> better prouided for But, <hi>Quid leges, ſine moribus?</hi> The miſerable
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16794:21"/>
euent and calamitie of all Churches ſheweth, that the gate being once ſet open to their auarice, it was too late to ſhut the wicket: yet the Popes of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding times were not altogether neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in ſeconding this ordinance of their predeceſſors. For <hi>Petrus Rebuffus</hi> ſayth, That in thoſe Appropriations which paſſe immediatly from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> this clauſe or the like is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes added in the end. <hi>Reſeruata ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De congrua por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. nu.</hi> 103.</note> 
               <hi>de fructibus, &amp; prouentibus huiuſmodi pro vno vel duobus Vicarijs perpetuis Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicè inſtituendis congruâ portione, ex qua ijdem vicarij poſsint de caetero ſuſtentari, iura Epiſcopalia ſoluere, &amp; alia incumbentia onera commodè ſupportare, non obſtantibus exemptionibus, priuilegijs, aut alijs quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe. <hi>Reſeruantes tamen de ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rax. Bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiaria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ript. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>fructibus &amp; prouentibus Beneficiorum ipſorum, ſi Eccleſiae parochiales fuerint, pro ſingulis perpetuis vicarijs in ſingulis eiſdem parochialibus Eccleſiis inſtituendis, portiones</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:16794:22"/>
               <hi>ex quibus dicti vicarij congruè ſuſtentari valeant, &amp; alia ſibi incumbentia onera ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo in all <hi>Confirmations</hi> granted from that See, of Appropriations made by inferiour Biſhops, the ſame clauſe or the like in effect was euer vſed, ſo ſaith <hi>Speculator. In confirmatione de Eccleſiis in proprios vſus retinendis ponitur</hi> haec clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſula. <note place="margin">Speculator <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tit. de confirma.</note> 
               <hi>Ita tamen, quod perpetuo vicario qui pro tempore ſeruiet in eadem, ad ſustentatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſuam, &amp; ſubeunda epiſcopalia &amp; Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae onera congrua portio de ipſius prouenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus relinquatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which clauſes of <hi>Reſeruation,</hi> it is manifeſt, That the Popes meaning was to haue the Vicar firſt prouided for, and to giue the ſurpluſage onely to the Monkes, as the ſame <hi>Rebuffus</hi> ſayth. And <hi>Panormitan</hi> alſo affirmeth, That <note place="margin">Panormit. ad c. de Monachis, extra de Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend.</note> thoſe which haue Churches granted vnto them in <hi>proprios vſus,</hi> cannot by vertue thereof challenge the whole fruits vnto themſelues, <hi>ſed reditus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:16794:22"/>
               <hi>ſuperfluos, detracta prius congruâ por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione pro Vicario ſeu Rectore ibidem inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuendo.</hi> So that if there be ſufficiencie for both, each may haue a ſhare: but if one muſt goe without, in all reaſon, the daily waiter ought to be firſt prouided for. And becauſe there are many things ordained in the <hi>Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> law which yet are not receiued for <hi>Canons,</hi> nor obeyed as lawes in all places, therfore will I ſhew vnto the world, that the practiſe of our Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times agreed with this very praeſcript and Rule of the <hi>Canon</hi> Law. For I haue ſeene the extract of a certaine Impropriation bearing date Ann. 1387. made by the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> of the <hi>Rectory</hi> of <hi>Erchford</hi> to the <hi>Abbeſſe</hi> and <hi>Couent</hi> of Saint <hi>Maries</hi> in the Citie of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> running in this maner. <hi>Saluâ portione pro <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icario dictae Eccleſiae hacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus aſsignata, &amp; per nos propter eius exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem &amp; inſufficientiam, &amp; alias cauſas legitimas moderatè augmentanda, praefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:16794:23"/>
               <hi>Eccleſiam Parochialem de Erchford, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the end thereof. <hi>Haec autem omnia &amp; ſingula ſtatuimus, &amp; finaliter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finimus ſaluâ nobis &amp; ſucceſſoribus noſtris liberâ facultate praemiſsa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe I haue ſeene another of the Rectorie of <hi>Shapwick</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Dorſet</hi> made by the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> to the Kings Chappel in <hi>Winburne</hi> Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the ſame Countie, with this clauſe. <hi>Reſeruantes tamen nobis &amp; ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus noſtris liberam poteſtatem portiones dictae Vicariae quoties neceſſarium, vel op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunum eſse videbitur diminuendi, &amp; ſi oportuerit, augmentandi, ſupplendi, immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo of the Rectory of <hi>Collſhill</hi> in the County of <hi>Berks</hi> with this clauſe. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruata prius de dictis fructibus &amp; prouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ad arbitrium nostrum vel ſucceſſorum nostrorum pro perpetuo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icario ibidem Domino ſeruituro, congruâ portione, ex qua idem vicarius commodé valeat ſustentari,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:16794:23"/>
               <hi>iura Epiſcopalia ſoluere, &amp; alia incumben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia onera ſupportare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for <hi>Ireland,</hi> I haue ſeene a Grant made by the Biſhop of <hi>Kildare</hi> of the Rectory of <hi>Cloncurry</hi> and ſundry other Churches of the ſame Dioceſſe, to the Abbey of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> neere <hi>Dublin,</hi> by way of Appropriation, in the end whereof I finde alwaies this clauſe added, <hi>Saluâ ſuſtentatione <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum eiſdem Eccleſiis deſeruientium.</hi> And without this or the like clauſe of <hi>ſauing</hi> and <hi>reſeruing</hi> to the Vicar, haue I not ſeene any vnion or appropriation made in either Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew yet further, that our Biſhops haue not onely in words reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to themſelues this power, but alſo in deed executed the ſame vpon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that without any former reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and onely in pure right of Law, I ſhall deſire credit in reporting what I haue ſeene in an old <hi>liger booke</hi> belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <note place="margin">Regastrum St. Thoma in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Breminghams Tour Dublin.</note> to the Abbey of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16794:24"/>
neere <hi>Dublin,</hi> and is to be found in <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minghams</hi> Tower in <hi>Dublin,</hi> wherein (among other <hi>Records)</hi> there is one <hi>fol.</hi> 50. which beareth this title. <hi>Ordinatio portionum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icariorum in Midia.</hi> By the tenor whereof, and by that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth it appeareth; That vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie mooued betweene the Biſhop of <hi>Meath</hi> on the one partie, and the Abbat and Conuent of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Dublin</hi> on the other, which held many Benefices in that Dioceſſe, and made ſmall allowance to the Curats, The Pope directed his commiſſion to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Delegates in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to heare and determine the caſe betweene them. The Biſhop alleadged among other things, That whereas they by law could not ſerue the cure of thoſe Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes themſelues, yet they would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their Vicars for inſtitution, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him as Ordinary to taxe the Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages. The <hi>Monkes</hi> in their anſwere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, That thoſe Churches were paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16794:24"/>
to them <hi>pleno iure,</hi> without any ſuch reſeruation of Taxing by the Biſhop, and that they had ſo held them time out of minde, with the knowledge, and without impeachment of the Biſhop, and thereupon pleaded a praeſcription in barre of the Biſhops iuriſdiction. Notwithſtanding all which, the Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates ordered, that the inſtitution of Vicars in thoſe ſeuerall Churches, and the taxe of their allowance, ſhould be left to the diſcretion and arbitrement of the Biſhop: who thereupon (the Abbat ſubmitting himſelfe and his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent to the order) proceeded in this manner. <hi>Ordinamus quod in Eccleſia de Rathtoth ordinetur vicarius, cui vicaria aſsignetur, ad aeſtimationem quindecim Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum.</hi> And ſo goeth forward, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting many other perpetuall Vicars in ſeuerall Pariſh Churches, and making them certaine allowances by way of taxe, which remaine vnto this day. Neither doe I doubt but that vpon diligent ſearch made in ſuch like <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16794:25"/>
               <hi>bookes</hi> of other diſſolued houſes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more examples and precedents of like nature might bee found. But by that which hath beene ſaid it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently appeare, That this power of ordaining Vicars in theſe appropriated Benefices, and taxing the rates of their allowances, is ſo faſt nailed to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops See, and ſo inherent in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that no priuiledge, no exemption, no preſcription, is able to diſpoſſeſſe him of it.</p>
            <p>And as this right of ordaining Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars in appropriated Churches, and tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their allowances out of the Fruits, is bodily ſetled in the Biſhop, ſo the right of claiming and receiuing the ſame is ſo deepely rooted in the perſon of the Vicar, that nothing but iniuſtice and ſacriledge can take it from him. For howſoeuer this falleth out otherwiſe in practiſe (ſuch was the corruption of former times, ſuch is of ours) yet in law, this is an infallible, and vnmooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16794:25"/>
foundation, That notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all grants, duties, rights, priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or other deuiſes whatſoeuer, yet the Church is ſtill to bee kept <hi>in ſtatu quo prius.</hi> And therefore <hi>Clement</hi> the third giueth this as a reaſon of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree aboue mentioned. <hi>Nolentes autem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D. C. ſicut de ſupple. neglige. Prelatorum.</note> 
               <hi>vt ſtatus Eccleſiae antiquus &amp; debitus per inſolentiam alicuius ſubuertatur Manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Innocentius</hi> giueth this as a leſſon. <hi>Epiſcopus nunquam debet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentire</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Innoce. ad D C. de monachis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra de praebend.</note> 
               <hi>quod red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus ſoliti Clericorum mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur: &amp; niſi ita prouideatur, quod hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitatem ſeruare poſsint, &amp; de iuribus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcepalibus reſpondere.</hi> And therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rebuff. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruâ portio. nu.</hi> 104.</note> learned Author alſo ſaith; <hi>Non potest Epiſcopus, vel alius donare vnius Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae temporalia Monaſterio, vel alteri in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructionem &amp; praeiudicium, primae Eccleſiae; nec vnum altare d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcooperire, vt alterum cooperiat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to make this cleere by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar caſes in the Law: <hi>Commendams</hi> (which, though not vtterly and in all
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16794:26"/>
caſes to be condemned, yet <hi>Rebuffus,</hi> ſeeing the great exceſſe and abuſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the place where he liued, calleth <hi>Pernitiem &amp; exitium totius Reipublicae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rebuff Prax. Benefic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tit. a Common.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtianae,</hi> becauſe they are neuer gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but with ſome nuiſance to the Church) were anciently wont to paſſe with this clauſe. <hi>Volumus aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rebuff. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>huiuſmodi Commendam, diuinus cultus et ſolitus Monachorum &amp; miniſtroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, numerus in dicto Monaſterio nullatenus minuatur, ſed illius &amp; illorum congrué ſupportentur onera conſueta; De refiduis vero Monaſterij fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus &amp; reditibus &amp; prouentibus dispone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; ordinare libere &amp; licitè valeas, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like to be vnderſtood, &amp; much rather of the Vicar, in caſe a ſingle Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice were ſo granted. For in his caſe (as <hi>Panormitan</hi> reporteth) though no <note place="margin">Panorm. ad d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de monachis.</note> ſuch clauſe were expreſſed in fauour of him; yet the Law of a <hi>Commendam</hi> will giue the <hi>Commendatarie</hi> no more, then the remainder of the fruits, after the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars allowance made, and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16794:26"/>
charges borne, and duties paied: whereof he maketh bold to put the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Cardinals in mind; and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe <hi>Commendataries</hi> with <hi>Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries,</hi> ſaith, that neither of them both <hi>Potest immutare ſtatum Eccleſiae; vnde debent facere deſeruire, per Clericos ſeu nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merum Clericorum conſuetum, &amp; hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ibi more ſolito ſeruare.</hi> Againe, the Biſhop or other Viſitor is ſo rooted in Law for the receiuing of his procurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons due for viſitation, that no cuſtome, no Grant of Predeceſſor, nor ought elſe, but a priuiledge from the Pope, which was a Tranſcendent aboue all right and reaſon, could take it from him; yet in caſe that by any occaſion the profits of the Benefice come to bee diminiſhed, the Biſhop muſt either in part or in whole forgoe them, and take as the Church is able to ſpare them. <hi>Et pro modo facultatum Eccleſiae</hi> (as <hi>Ludouicus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ludouic. Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Conſil.</hi> 369.</note> 
               <hi>Romanus</hi> ſaith.) And <hi>Hoſtienſis</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that in this caſe the viſitor muſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16794:27"/>
beare his owne charges: <hi>Eſt enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>de mente &amp; verbis iuris, quod Eccleſia vltra poſſe non grauetur</hi> (as <hi>Panormitan</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeth him.) And albeit they both ſpake in caſe, where more Viſitors fall vpon the Dioceſſe in the ſame yeere; and all looke for Procurations: yet <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Anchoranus</hi> ſaith, that it is the ſame, <hi>Si vel vnus procurandus fuerit: Ideò enim</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author) <hi>bona dignitatis ſuae Epiſcopo ſunt attributa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer a Patron which foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and endoweth a Church may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vnto himſelfe a yeerely Penſion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>C.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>extra de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſibus.</hi>
               </note> to bee payd out of the ſame Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Notwithſtanding, if by any accident the other reuenues of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rebuff de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſeſſ. nu.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>28.</note> Church fall out to be ſo ſhort that they cannot conueniently and competently maintaine the Incumbent, the Patron muſt in this caſe forbeare his right, not as if it were now taken from him, but as if it had bin <hi>tacita conditio,</hi> and ſo to be vnderſtood from the beginning. And
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16794:27"/>
therefore <hi>Panormitan</hi> ſaith, That that power of reſeruing a penſion vpon the Endowment of a Benefice muſt be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, <hi>Quando fructus ſunt abundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; ſufficientes Clerico.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like is to bee ſaid, If a Biſhop ſhould reſerue a penſion out of a fatte <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Rebuff. Tracta de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cif. poſſeſſo nu.</hi> 134. <hi>&amp; nu.</hi> 141:</note> &amp; wealthie Benefice to the vſe of a Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or other Clerke. (a cuſtome much vſed heretofore in <hi>England,</hi> but taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way afterwards by Act of Parliament) For if either by errour at the firſt the penſion was ſo great, or afterwards the remainder grew to be ſo little, that the Incumbent was not able to maintaine himſelfe of that which did remaine, the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ludouic. Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> conſil.</hi> 369.</note> penſion was either to bee abated, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken cleane away, to the end the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent might be ſtill prouided for.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, to inſtance in a caſe or two concerning theſe very <hi>Monkes</hi> of whom wee ſpeake, The <hi>Pope</hi> was wont heretofore to grant large Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges to <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16794:28"/>
non-paiment of Tithes: ſo long as they benefited themſelues, without enormous hurt vnto the Churches, it was tolerated: But if they either beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or bought the whole or greateſt part of the Pariſh, and ſo their priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>De non decimando,</hi> grew ouer hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Parſon, the <hi>Monkes</hi> were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to growe of themſelues to a new compoſition with the Incumbent, and to diſclaime the rigour of their Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Reuocatur enim priuilegium, fi ex</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Extra de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileg.</note> 
               <hi>post facto incipit enormiter eſſe nociuum,</hi> ſaith the Law.</p>
            <p>Neither were the <hi>Popes</hi> leſſe prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall in granting them priuiledges, <hi>De percipiendis Decimis,</hi> whereby they were authoriſed to receiue the Tithes of Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes vnto themſelues without any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation or vnion of the Churches: yet in this caſe alſo <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth publiſhed a Decree of all ſuch priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in this manner. <hi>Vbi autem per huiuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi> 
               <note place="margin">C. Statuto. de decim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in ſexto</note> 
               <hi>Conceſsiones decimarum, parochiales Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:16794:28"/>
               <hi>adeò grauari contingit, quod earum Rectores de ipſarum Reditibus congruè ſustentari, &amp; commode iura Epiſcopalia ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibere non poſsint; prouideatur per Locorum Ordinarios, &amp; ordinetur taliter, quod ijſdem Rectoribus tantum de illarum relinquatur prouentibus, quod exinde competentem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentationem habeant, &amp; Epiſcopalia iur a ſoluere valeant, alia<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> onera debitè ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then the Law be ſo carefull of the Curate and actuall Incumbent, or day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſter of the Church, as to reuoke Priuiledges, to take away Penſions, to debarre the Patron of his right and to leſſen the profits of <hi>Commendataries,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then hee ſhall want; much more then may it be thought, that it will not ſuffer the <hi>Monke,</hi> who was neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to better then a Drone, by vertue of an Appropriation, to eat vp the ſweet of the Bee, that is, the neceſſary mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the labouring Prieſt and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpell. And if the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16794:29"/>
               <hi>Biſhops,</hi> which are <hi>de iure diuino,</hi> ſuffer their owne hands to bee tied, in receiuing their dueties from the <hi>Curate,</hi> where it cannot well be ſpared, much more ought the <hi>Monke,</hi> who was neuer a man of Gods making, but a meere creature of the <hi>Pope,</hi> who alſo may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make them all againe at his pleaſure, (as <hi>Felinus</hi> ſaith) bee forced to make him a more liberall allowance out of that, which of right wholy belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to him, for his dayly ſeruice in the Church. For in this and all other caſes of this ſort, where the profits of the <hi>Curate</hi> are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, and diuerted anoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r way, the Rule preſcribed in the 9. Councill of <hi>Toledo</hi> is to bee obſerued, namely, <hi>Vt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il. Tolet</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>q</hi> 2 <hi>c. Bona Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conſultum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>haec temperamenti aequitas obſeruetur, quod cui tribuit, competens ſubſidium conferat, cui to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ic, grauia damna non infligat.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall it bee amiſſe, by the way, to let the world know what this <hi>Councill</hi> in thoſe dayes thought to bee <hi>Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens ſubſidium.</hi> i. a competent reliefe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16794:29"/>
vnto the poore <hi>Monkes,</hi> and what to be, <hi>graue damnum,</hi> vnto the Churches. The words of the Councel are theſe, <hi>Quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis Epiſcoporum in parochiâ ſuâ Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>D. C.</hi> 5. <hi>Concil. tolet.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>construere forte voluerit, &amp; hoc ex rebus Eccleſiae, cui praefidet ditare decreuerit, non amplius quam quinquage ſimam partem dare debebit, vt haec temperamenti, &amp;c. vt ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In thoſe daies a penſion of the fifti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth part vnto the <hi>Monkes</hi> was thought a burthen heauy enough to bee laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Churches, whereas now adaies, and ſince thoſe appropriations came vp, ſcantly is the fifteenth part left for the Miniſters of the Churches; ſo farre are wee gone from the temper by them preſcribed; which temper had it beene obſerued heretofore in this Realme of <hi>Ireland,</hi> neither ſhould there haue beene ſo many Abbeis here erected with the ruine of the Churches, nor ſhould the <hi>Monks</hi> haue ſpent that in luxurie which ſhould haue ſerued for the neceſſity of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16794:30"/>
the Preacher. But euery Church ſhould haue beene prouided, if not of a rich, yet of a conuenient maintenance, and conſequently, if not of an excellent, yet of a reaſonably learned Miniſter.</p>
            <p>And to go forward with the courſe of the Eccleſiaſticall Law in this point, as it was in force at the time of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and to ſhew how carefull the Popes and Prelates of thoſe daies were, to mend a fault which themſelues had made, and to daube vp that gaping and irreparable breach which they had made vpon the Church, in appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her liuing and reuenues to the <hi>Monkes,</hi> by prouiding a perpetuall competencie for the Vicar, It is further to be noted, that if this allowance, were once made, and yet afterwards came to bee impaired, and leſſe then enough, it was ſtill made good againe vnto him out of the Appropriation. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, If the Vicars part conſiſted in a certaine kind, as in haie; and the owner
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16794:30"/>
ſhould afterwards conuert the ground to tillage: If it were to ariſe out of certaine mens lands, and they ſhould afterwards plead and prooue a priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>de non decimando:</hi> If by warre or any other occaſion it came to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct: For in all theſe caſes, the Vicar is to ſue to the Ordinarie for a new al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, and he is to make it out of the remainder of the fruits in the Abbats hand, ſo ſaith <hi>Felinus, Bonis deperditis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De offic. Vicar.</note> 
               <hi>Vicario aſsignatis, Index ei de aliis proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere debet.</hi> And <hi>Rebuffus. Si portio fuit destructa &amp; extincta bello, vel alio caſu,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De congr. port.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; adhuc fructus ſufficientes remanent apud Rectorem vel Patronum, eo caſu adhuc iterum perenda est congrua portio inſtar illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us qui legitimam conſumpſit, vt de filio pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digo est in Euang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence it is alſo that <hi>Panormitan, Felinus,</hi> and other <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> deliuer this for a ruled caſe in law, That if any ſhall implead the Vicar for any part of his portion, the Proprietary or Rector,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16794:31"/>
may alſo come in for his intereſt, by way of aſſiſtance vnto the Vicar, <hi>Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Felinus ad C. G. Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arius ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra de fide In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument.</note> 
               <hi>praeiudicij quod ſibi ex contrario euentu litis poſsit irrogari, cum perditis bonis Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carii, oporteret prouideri de aliis bonis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ſhewed before, that our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> were wont to reſerue vnto themſelues a power of encreaſing or altering the Vicars por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at their owne diſcretion. Neither was it materiall whether this compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie beeing prouided for the Vicar, there were ought or nought remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Proprietary or <hi>Monke:</hi> for if the whole tithes would ſerue but for the Vicar, the <hi>Monke</hi> was to goe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: for from the beginning the tithes belonged to the Church, whoſe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Paſtor the Vicar is; neither were they giuen but for the daylie office in the Church, which office the Vicar doth: and if nothing bee left vnto the Proprietary, yet are his wages anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16794:31"/>
to his paines. And as one ſaith, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius agit de damno vitando, Monaſterium verò de lucro captando; ideò praefertur Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia vicarij, monasterio.</hi> And reaſon good; for the Vicaris the labouring oxe which treadeth out the corne, whoſe mouth muſt not be muſled, as ſaith the law of God.</p>
            <p>And for the further cleering of this whole point, it is to be obſerued, that whatſoeuer hath hitherto beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning the Vicar, it is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not of a <hi>Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porarie,</hi> but of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Vicar, which is a perſon foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in law, without a new Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: and is in the Canon Law, and by the Canoniſts called <hi>Parochialis Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, Parochialis Eccleſiae Sacerdos, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Eccleſiae, Perpetuus Eccleſiae Presbyter, vel vicarius,</hi> not to be appointed by the Abbat, and licenced by the Biſhop to ſay ſeruice; but to be preſented by the Patron, what euer he be, and to receiue Canonicall <hi>Inſtitution</hi> at the hands of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16794:32"/>
the <hi>Ordinarie</hi> of the place. And as the Biſhop is not onely authoriſed, but alſo commanded, and <hi>ſub obteſtatione diuini Iudicij</hi> by the Law required, not to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a Preſentee, vnleſſe the Preſentor ſhall firſt aſſigne and lay foorth a legall portion of the profits for his mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and may <hi>ex officio</hi> proceed ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as the cauſe ſhall ſo require. So alſo hath the Vicar his action to implead the Parſon, if either it was not aſſigned from the beginning, or if it fall out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to be inſufficient, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron refuſe to ſupplie, and to make it good againe vnto him. And therefore <hi>Hoſtienfis,</hi> the queſtion being put, <hi>Quod ius habeat Vicarius in Eccleſia?</hi> among <note place="margin">Hostien. in ſumma. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffic. Vicar.</note> many others, putteth this for one. <hi>Item habet ius petendi congruam portionem de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditibus Eccleſiae, cui ſeruit ſi minus idoneam habeat.</hi> The Action which he is to bring is called, <hi>Actio ſecundum Canonem;</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to that which we call an <hi>Action vpon the Statute;</hi> and is then brought,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16794:32"/>
when a man is priuately intereſſed in the breach of a <hi>Canon,</hi> and yet hath no ſpeciall Action giuen him thereby. And this Action lieth, Whether the Patron or other Receiuer of the Tithes, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt or not exempt, Religious or Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, Monke or Canon, Clerke or Laike: For in this caſe there is no exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but whoſoeuer receiueth the profits is liable to the Action. And therefore I will ſay as a learned <hi>Canoniſt</hi> hath ſaid before me, <hi>Cum in hoc caſu neminem Inueniam priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giatum, illi dare priuilegium non est mihi libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Et ideò omnes tenentur ad hanc Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem qui decimas &amp; Beneficij fructus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Action is to be brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Biſhop or Ordinarie of the place, as one which ſtandeth principally charged with this dutie. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in <hi>France</hi> their high <hi>Sedentarie Courts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> though temporall, yet vſe to lend a helping hand vnto the Vicar in this caſe, and are often ſued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16794:33"/>
The reaſon is, becauſe the Biſhops ſtand aſmuch in feare in thoſe places of offending thoſe mighty <hi>Societies,</hi> as ours doe of <hi>Prohibition</hi> and <hi>Praemunire.</hi> And therefore <hi>Iohannes Andraeas</hi> ſaith merily <note place="margin">Iohan. Andrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ad c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra, de Rebus Eccleſiae non a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enand.</note> of them: That,</p>
            <q>Cum ſint cornuti non audent cornibus vti.</q>
            <p>Meaning, that they dare not vſe that power which the Law giueth them in this caſe: yet the Eccleſiaſticall Iudges vſe to repine at this vſurpation of the Parliaments: And the Popes as well to ſupplie the negligence of the Biſhops, as to giue the Parliament no occaſion to treſpaſſe vpon their Iuriſdiction, vſe to giue in charge to thoſe which are called <hi>Conſeruatores Apoſtolici,</hi> in ſpeciall to take knowledge of the Vicars portion. To theſe their Vicars, if either their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance be in it ſelfe too ſmall, or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthened with Penſions, and other payments, vſe to reſort, and by them haue they remedie againſt the <hi>Monkes</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:16794:33"/>
and others. And for poofe heereof <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Rebuffus</hi> ſaith, That himſelfe hath beene often called to counſell in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of theſe portions for the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car: which could not be, vnleſſe the caſe were cleere, and void of al doubt in law: for vpon the leaſt doubt or demurrer in law that could ariſe, the <hi>Conſeruators</hi> hands were cloſed, and they forbidden to proceed, as men appointed for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe onely of ſuch apparant iniuries as theſe were. Happy Vicars, where ſo many men of greateſt place ſtriue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, who ſhall bee moſt forward to do them right.</p>
            <p>There is alſo with vs ſome contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about them and their liuings, but it is not who ſhall do them good.</p>
            <p>But what doe I ſtand, either to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the right, or to lament the wrong of our poore <hi>Vicars,</hi> or to declare the Iuriſdiction of the <hi>Ordinarie</hi> in theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by proofes and arguments taken out of the <hi>Canon</hi> lawe, ſeeing that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16794:34"/>
hath hitherto been ſaid which hath not been long ſince acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, approoued, and confirmed by the Common Law of theſe Kingdomes? To let paſſe many others, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in one for all. There is a <hi>Caſe</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported <hi>Term. Michael. An.</hi> 2. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 10. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Termino Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael. in</hi> 2 <hi>H</hi> 4. fol 10. <hi>Caſ.</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>Caſ.</hi> 44. which ſeemeth a Briefe of all that hitherto hath been ſayd, and is as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Abbey of</hi> Saltaſh <hi>in the County of</hi> Deuon. <hi>was appropriated to the Colledge of</hi> Wind or. <hi>And vpon the Appropriation the Vicar that then was, endowed with certaine Houſes for his entertainment, to the valew of twenty pounds</hi> per ann. <hi>by the Ordinary, and by all thoſe which had interest therein. And moreouer tooke an Oath, and was alſo bound in a great ſumme of money before the Collector of the Pope in</hi> England <hi>with the aſſent of the Ordinarie, to bee paid into the Chamber of the Pope, vpon condition that hee ſhould hold himſelfe content with the ſayd Endowment, and ſhould neuer will the</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:16794:34"/>
               <hi>contrary: neither ſhould procure any thing, or doe any thing againſt the ſaid endowment, or to the diſanulling thereof: nor ſhould euer claime any more to belong to his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icarage, but ſhould hold himſelfe to the paiment of the ſayd Endowment. And if hee failed in the ſaid Conditions, or in any one of them, that then hee ſhould incurre the paine of the ſaid ſumme to the Chamber of the Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Afterwards came the Deane of the ſayd Colledge into the Kings Chancerie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared this matter, and further auerred, That the ſayd Vicar had claimed another Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, contrarie to the Endowment made by the Ordinary of the place, and contrary to his Oath. And that the Vicar vpon ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion made, That the Pleas of Couenant and Debts ariſing of Contracts within the Realme belonged to the Kings Court, had purchaſed a Prohibition directed to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour. And hereupon aſwell the Collector as the Deane prayed a Conſultation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here wee ſee, firſt, that not onely the Reſeruation of a <hi>Vicarage</hi> vpon an
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16794:35"/>
Appropriation, but alſo the Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof belongeth to the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the place. Secondly, that the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car</hi> bringeth his action againſt the Deane, which was the proprietary of the Tithes, by vertue of the <hi>Impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Thirdly, that hee brought this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a ſecond <hi>Taxation;</hi> as either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the firſt to haue been too little from the beginning; or ſhewing that it had been abated or diminiſhed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; whether by chance of fire, or falling of Rents, or lacke of Tenants, or by ſome other accident: And laſtly, That this Action was brought before the <hi>Ordinarie</hi> of the place: For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon was the Conſultation prayed, but vpon a Prohibition granted out of the Kings Court? wherupon was the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition granted but vpon the Deanes action, brought before the Collector of the Pope? And whereupon ſhould the <hi>Vicar</hi> be ſued vpon breach of Oath and Bond before the Collector, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16794:35"/>
claime of a new <hi>Taxation</hi> before him which made the old <hi>i</hi> before the Biſhop.</p>
            <p>Neither can it bee ſaid that this is a Caſe, and not a Iudgement, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prooueth nothing. For the <hi>Caſe</hi> being ſo put, there was no exception ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; neither againſt the <hi>Vicar,</hi> that hee had not, <hi>perſonam ſtandi in iudicio,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet againſt the Biſhop, that he had not iuriſdiction in theſe caſes, (for theſe exceptions had been peremptory if they had been true) neither yet that the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment once made, it ought not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to bee increaſed in fauour of the <hi>Vicar.</hi> Onely the Deane granting all this, ſued the poore <hi>Vicar</hi> before the Collector for breach of <hi>Oath,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of his <hi>Bond:</hi> For this was euer the policie of that kind of men, to ſecure themſelues both fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore <hi>Vicars</hi> lawful claim, &amp; from the ordinary Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Biſhop, by ſome collaterall and indirect ſecuritie. As for example, in a Caſe before mentioned betweene the Biſhop of <hi>Meath</hi> and the Abbat of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16794:36"/>
               <hi>S. Thomas.</hi> The Abbat got the Biſhop to bee bound in a Bond of a thouſand pounds, neuer after that to trouble the <hi>Monkes</hi> with a new <hi>Taxation.</hi> And here wee ſee the <hi>Vicar</hi> tyed, not onely in a Bond of a great ſumme, but alſo by a ſolemne Oath, neuer afterwards to claime a new Endowment: which needed not, had not the Lawes of the Land agreed with the Lawes of the Church in fauour of the diſtreſſed <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car.</hi> But the Deuill, I thinke, was in thoſe men, onely to ruine the Church and Chriſtian Religion by them.</p>
            <p>But to make theſe points yet more apparant according to the courſe of the Common Law. It may not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, That anciently in theſe Kingdoms, the Vicars right was much challenged in the Kings Courts for bringing Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his owne name, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parſon But the Parliament (as it ſeemeth) being informed of this miſchiefe, and ſeeing the miſery which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16794:36"/>
the Vicars fell into hereby, prouided for them by a Statute Anno 14. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. cap. 17. wherein it is ordained, That Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An</hi> 14 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</note> may bring their Writs of <hi>Iuris v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum,</hi> or recouer by any other Writ aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as the Parſon might. And this was it which not long after, namely Anno 40. of the ſame King, in a Caſe reported Term. Trinitat. Caſ. 15. fol. 28. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Term. Trinitat. caſ.</hi> 15. <hi>fol.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Fincheden</hi> ſaid, That it was true, that in ancient times the opinion was, <hi>That the Vicar ſhould not haue action againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> but, <hi>I finde</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that this is changed for the better:</hi> which (as <hi>Brooke</hi> ſaith) <hi>Nemo dedixit:</hi> i. no man gainſaid. <note place="margin">Abridgement. tit. Vicars.</note> And conſequently it was then taken to be cleere in Law. And as touching the Iuriſdiction of the <hi>Ordinarie</hi> in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding for the Vicars maintenance, <hi>Belknappe</hi> in debating the ſame Caſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth theſe wordes: <hi>Wee haue theſe lands aſsigned to the Vicar by the aſsent of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie: And you will grant that the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie may encreaſe or diminiſh his portion,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:16794:37"/>
               <hi>hauing regard vnto the charge which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vnto him:</hi> which <hi>Fincheden</hi> there granteth to be true, in caſe the Vicars eſtate become weake and feeble: And we deſire no more. And in this caſe, although the Parſon or Proprietarie be ſaide to be intereſſed; yet is all the power and right of aſſigning the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment in the Biſhops hand. For (as <hi>Belknapp</hi> there ſaith) <hi>The Ordinarie ſhall endow, and the Parſon ſhall doe nothing but conſent, becauſe the thing it ſelfe is meerely spirituall.</hi> In which caſe, if the Parſon will not conſent, yet the Biſhop goeth on without him. And if (perchance) he ſhall exceede in his taxe, the Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etarie is left to his Appeale, <hi>ab exceſsiua taxatione,</hi> by the courſe of the Canon Law, as <hi>Rebuffus</hi> ſaith: But other reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die he hath none, no not at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, as <hi>Belknapp</hi> there affirmeth. And it is further to bee remembred, that this power of aſſigning the Vicars portion, euen out of the lands and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16794:37"/>
poſſeſſions of the <hi>Abbat,</hi> as Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the place, was euer helde ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Biſhop, that he might doe it <hi>ſans Congé, ſans licence du Roy:</hi> i. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaue or licence of the King, as is there affirmed: And therefore ſhall not now need a new Acte of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for his warrant, but onely the hand of iuſtice, for his aſſiſtance in the execution of his right.</p>
            <p>It ſhould ſeeme, that about the times of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3. <hi>Rich.</hi> the 2. and <hi>Hen.</hi> the 4. which was an age of horrible confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by reaſon of thoſe bloudie warres wherein the Crowne of <hi>England</hi> was then entangled both at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; the greater fiſh of the Clergie went about to eat vp the leſſer. My rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe in thoſe dayes there were ſo many ſolemne lawes made to maintaine the one in his right, and to repreſſe the iniury of the other. For ill cuſtomes commonly giue occaſion to make good lawes. In the time of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:16794:38"/>
the 3. (as hath been formerly ſaid) there was a Statute made, to enable the Vicar to bring his Action againſt the Abbat, who detained the Glebe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duties from him. In the time of <hi>Richard</hi> the 2. anno 15. a Statute was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 15. <hi>Richar.</hi> 2.</note> made, That in euery Licence from thenceforth to be made out of <hi>Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> of the Appropriations of any Pariſh Church it ſhould expreſſely be contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and compriſed, That the <hi>Dioceſan</hi> of the place, vpon the Appropriation of ſuch Churches, ſhould ordaine, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the valuation of ſuch Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, a conuenient ſumme of money to be payd and diſtributed yeerely out of the Fruits and profits of the ſame Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, by thoſe which haue them in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vſe, and by their ſucceſſors, to the poore Parochians of the ſaid Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in aide of their ſuſtenance and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for euer. And alſo that the Vicar ſhould be well and ſufficiently endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. cap. 6. Alſo by a Statute of 4. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <note place="margin">4. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.</note>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:16794:38"/>
It was ordained, that the Statute of 15. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2 ſhould be kept, and put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. And that Appropriations made ſince that Statute, contrary thereunto, ſhould be reformed by a certaine time, or elſe be void: And that from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth in euery Church ſo appropria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, a Secular perſon ſhould be ordained a Vicar perpetuall, canonically inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and inducted in the ſame, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenably endowed by the diſcretion of the Ordinarie, to doe diuine Seruice, and to informe the people, and to keep hoſpitalitie there, with other conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and limitations there expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Here we ſee firſt, That although the Parliament was carefull to haue the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car prouided for; yet it left the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe things vnto the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe. Secondly, in caſe the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop was defectiue in his firſt Aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Vicars portion, hee was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to reforme it, and make it better by a time prefixed; otherwiſe his acte
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16794:39"/>
of Appropriation to be void. That the meaſure of the Endowment was to be conuenably, ſufficiently, and well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed. That there was no other Rule of this meaſure, but the diſcretion of the Biſhop, for the vſes mentioned in the Law. That this Vicar muſt be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, perpetuall, canonically inſtituted and inducted, all ſuitable to that which hath beene formerly declared out of the Canon Law. The fruit of all which Statutes is, That throughout the Church of <hi>England</hi> a man ſhall ſcarce finde an Impropriation without a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carage, or a Vicar without a reaſonable good allowance. And laſtly we finde, That beſides this reaſonable and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient allowance due vnto the Vicar, the Statute moſt wiſely and charitably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth that the <hi>Ordinarie</hi> ſhall ordaine a conuenient proportion of money, to be diſtributed yeerely among the poore of the Pariſh, meaning (as it ſeemeth) that euery bird taking his owne feather, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16794:39"/>
euery man his due, the <hi>Abbat</hi> ſhould be reduced to that ſmall penſion which was onely due vnto him at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by the law of Impropriations.</p>
            <p>THus haue I as plainly as I could, and as briefly as the matter would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, ſhewed, That out of euery Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice appropriate, there was euer a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent portion certaine, or vncertaine, by the Canon law due, and by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of all times and places, eſpecially of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> reſerued to the Vicar, for his daily ſeruice in the Church. Alſo that the Biſhop in his owne Dioceſſe, hath authoritie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Proprietarie to make this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance before hee admit of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentee: or vpon his refuſall or delay, to preſent in his owne right, as in other caſes of <hi>Lapſe</hi> and <hi>Deuolution:</hi> and out of the whole profits to make a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſufficient allowance for the Vicar, and to compell the Proprietary to performance thereof by excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16794:40"/>
And laſtly that both the right of the Vicar, and the power of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in theſe caſes haue euer been war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the Lawes and Statutes of the Kingdome. If then this was law here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, it is law ſtill, vnleſſe it be either expreſſely reuoked, or tacitely diſanul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſince the time of the diſſolution. And this is the point which commeth next to be diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>And truely for mine owne part, I muſt confeſſe, that I could neuer yet learne of any Statute made ſince the diſſolution in either Kingdome, which either tacitely or expreſſely doth whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abrogate, or in part derogate from the Canon lawes, and the laudable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and ancient Statutes of theſe Kingdomes in this point. And pitie were it, That the Lawes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, hauing left vnto the Church, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to this of <hi>Ireland,</hi> this onely boord, whereby to ſaue it ſelfe from the miſerable wrecke which it ſuffered
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16794:40"/>
by the ouerflowing Deluge and Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions</hi> and <hi>Impropriations</hi> in time of Poperie, the Parliament ſhould be thought guiltie of ſo great a ſinne, as to robbe her of this poore meanes, to ſaue her ſelfe withall. Rather it might be hoped, that being put in mind there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and if neede ſhould ſo require, they would more plainely expound their meaning, and in ſuch ſort, as might beſt ſtand with the glory of GOD, the good of the holy Church, the honour of ſo high a Court, and with the wiſedome of euery particular member thereof. But my purpoſe is not at this time, to perſwade a Parlament to make a Law; but to prooue vnto the world, That the Law is of force alreadie, and wanteth nothing but a fit and a willing hand to put it in execution. In purſuit of which point, I liſt not frame vnto my ſelfe an aduerſe partie: Rather I wiſh, that the iuſtice of the cauſe may neuer finde an enemie; Neither will I be curious in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16794:41"/>
forging Arguments againſt mine owne opinion, for that were but like tilting at a <hi>Sarazens</hi> head. Onely I will ſhew, that all thoſe Statutes which moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly concerne this matter, make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt, but altogether for the Vicars maintenance, in ſuch ſort as hath beene before declared; wiſhing and hoping alſo, That ſome religious Profeſſour of the Common Law, may hereafter vpon theſe poore grounds of mine, goe on, and maintaine this cauſe of GOD and of his Church, with more ſtrength of witt, and force of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then I am able to doe, in a point which doeth not ſo properly belong vnto mine owne profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The Statutes therefore that princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 31. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>in Ireland.</hi>
               </note> concerne this matter, are thoſe of 27. and 31. <hi>Henry</hi> 8. and 1. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. in <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe of 28. and 32. of <hi>Henry</hi> 8. heere in <hi>Ireland</hi> to the ſame effect. All made for the diſſoluing, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, ſurrendring, and taking into
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16794:41"/>
the Kings hands the <hi>Monaſteries, Free-Chappels,</hi> and other religious houſes in both theſe Kingdomes. In theſe Statutes it is intended, that the King ſhall haue and hold the ſaid <hi>Monasteries</hi> with their <hi>Parſonages</hi> appropriate, and other lands, in as large and ample man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme, as the late Abbat or Prior held them, at the time of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, ſuppreſsion, or other giuing vp of the ſame: for ſo ſay the Statutes. <hi>His Maieſtie ſhall haue and enioy to him and his heires for euer, all and ſingular ſuch Monasteries and tithes; and in as large and ample manner, as the Abbats now haue them, in the right of their Houſes.</hi> And in another place of the ſame Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute it is ſaid; <hi>That the Takers from the King, ſhall haue and hold all ſuch lands, &amp;c. And ſhall haue all ſuch Suites, Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Entries, &amp;c. in like manner, forme, and condition, &amp;c.</hi> And in another paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; <hi>That the King ſhall hold them in the ſame ſtate and condition as now they be, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:16794:42"/>
Which words of <hi>manner, forme, ſtate,</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> are not to bee reſtrained, as I conceiue, to the preſent and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all poſſeſsion of the Abbat, at the day of the diſſolution: but to the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall right which he had in the name of his Houſe. And therefore wee finde it ſometimes added in thoſe Statutes; <hi>Or of right ought to haue had, held, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied the ſame, at the time of the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For whether the Abbat had any thing vniuſtly detained from him, the King ſucceeding in his right, had acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to recouer it; becauſe the Abbat might, and of right ought to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered the ſame: Or whether the Abbat owed any thing to any man, or wrongfully detained from any man, the King or his Grantee, ſtanding ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his right, might bee impleaded for it, becauſe there was no more paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the King, then the Abbat ought of right to haue poſſeſſed. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the law chargeth the King with
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16794:42"/>
the paiment of all the due debts of the Abbats, or their Houſes, by the Statute 27. <hi>Henry</hi> 8. in <hi>England</hi> not printed. Whereas therefore it is ſaid, That the King ſhall hold thoſe lands and Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations, in the ſame manner, forme, and ſtate, as the Prior did at the time of the diſſolution; I take the meaning to be, that hee ſhall enioy them by vertue of that Act, with the ſame limitations, priuiledges, and burdens, as the Prior did. As for example. The <hi>Templars</hi> held their lands exempt from paiment of tithes, not ſimply, but <hi>ſub modo: ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet, quamdiu propriis manibus excoluntur:</hi> wherefore <hi>ſub eodem modo,</hi> and in the ſame forme and ſtate, the King doth, and ought, to hold thoſe lands exempt from paiment of tithes vnto this day. And that this is ſo, and that thoſe Acts of diſſolution did not onely looke to the preſent actuall eſtate of thoſe lands, but had an eye to the whole right of the Abbats, and to all future poſsibilities,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16794:43"/>
appeareth plainely by a Caſe of the 11. of the late Queene, reported by <hi>Dier.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">11. <hi>Elizabeth. Dier.</hi>
               </note> Where a Prior of a late diſſolued houſe of St. <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> had long before the diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, made a leaſe of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>D.</hi> for terme of yeeres vnto <hi>A.</hi> which <hi>A.</hi> beeing tenant, did pay tithes of the ſaid Mannor, to the Abbey of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi> Vpon the diſſolution, the King granted the reuerſion of the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in fee, vnto one <hi>Stathome</hi> and his heires. Afterwards the leaſe expired, and <hi>Stathome</hi> taking the land into his owne hands, refuſed to pay tithes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging, that the Mannor was paſſed to him, <hi>To haue and to hold the ſame in as ample manner as the Prior held it, &amp;c.</hi> And further declared in <hi>Chancery;</hi> That the ſaid Prior, ſo long as hee held it in his owne hands, was diſcharged from paiment of tithes, by a priuiledge from <hi>Rome,</hi> as all the <hi>Ciſtertians, Hoſpitalers,</hi> and <hi>Templars</hi> were. And vpon conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Statute of 27. <hi>Henry</hi> 8.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16794:43"/>
It was reſolued by <hi>Catlin, Saunders, Southcote,</hi> and <hi>Dier;</hi> and vpon their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion it was accordingly decreed by the Lord Keeper that then was, That the ſaid <hi>Stathome</hi> and his heires, ſhould hold the ſaid Mannor, diſcharged from paiment of tithes, <hi>Tanque a ceo, quils ceo leſſeront &amp; miſſeront a ferme; i.</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time as they ſhould let it out to farme: for <hi>ſub hoc modo</hi> was the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge granted to the Prior, and <hi>ſub eodem modo</hi> was the land to bee held by the King, and from him by <hi>Stathome</hi> and his heires. By the ſame reaſon, if at the time of the diſſolution, the Prior had held it in his owne hands, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently it had come to the King, and from him to <hi>Stathome,</hi> diſcharged from tithes in the beginning; yet if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he had let it out to a Farmer, his Farmer ſhould not at this day bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, becauſe the Priors farmer was to pay it, notwithſtanding the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And <hi>Stathome</hi> was to hold it,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16794:44"/>
               <hi>In ſuch and in like ample manner:</hi> True, but in no more ample manner then the Prior did. Now the Prior was to hold it diſcharged from paiment of tithes, no longer then while hee held it in his owne hands, therefore alſo <hi>Stathome</hi> ſhall hold it in the ſame manner, and with the ſame limitation.</p>
            <p>This haue I heard deliuered by men of good ſufficiency and skill in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawes.</hi> And <hi>Dier</hi> ſeemeth to auerre as much, when he ſaith; <hi>Tanque à ceo quils ceo leſſeront &amp; miſſeront à ferme.</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying thereby, That ſo ſoone as it ſhould fall into a Farmers hands, the priuiledge ſhould be ſuſpended, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not Simple, but Modall, and reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned onely to the perſon of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Lord or owner, not extended to his Farmer. And generally, looke what priuiledges the <hi>Abbats</hi> had concerning thoſe lands, the ſame are ſtill pleadable by the Takers from the King: and what burthens ſoeuer the <hi>Abbats</hi> were
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16794:44"/>
chargeable with, with the ſame are their Succeſſors at this day; for <hi>quoad hoc</hi> they ſtill retaine the nature of <hi>Abbey lands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence I conclude, That theſe words of <hi>manner, forme, ſtate</hi> and <hi>condition</hi> are not reſtrained to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and actuall poſſeſſion wherein thoſe lands were held at the time of the <hi>Suppreſsion:</hi> but doe comprehend the whole nature of their title, with all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges &amp; burthens whatſoeuer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto belonging, or in any wiſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining. And therefore to draw now vnto our purpoſe: Whereas vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Impropriation</hi> a conuenient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was heretofore reſerued for the Vicar, as hath beene before declared, which maintenance was to bee made good vnto him from time to time, by the <hi>Abbat</hi> or other Proprietarie, &amp; that out of the very fruits and reuenues of the Parſonage: It is manifeſt, That the <hi>Parſonage,</hi> in whoſe hands ſoeuer it bee
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16794:45"/>
found, remaineth ſtill chargeable with the ſame burthen. For <hi>Res tranfit cum ſua onere,</hi> and whoſoeuer now holdeth it, is to hold it in the ſame and like <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, forme, ſtate,</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> as the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or</hi> did. But the <hi>Prior</hi> held thoſe <hi>Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations</hi> with the charge of a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent maintenance to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar,</hi> at the diſcretion of the <hi>Ordinarie,</hi> therefore the <hi>Proprietarie</hi> that now is, is chargeable with the ſame, and is to bee impleaded for it, as the <hi>Prior</hi> was.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Statute</hi> is yet more plaine for the poore <hi>Vicars</hi> profit: For bee it that the Appropriation had beene paſſed to the King, and from him to his Grantee, without mention of ſuch <hi>manner, forme, ſtate,</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> as is before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited: yet afterwards the <hi>Statute</hi> addeth a full and perfect clauſe of <hi>Sauing</hi> and <hi>Reſeruing</hi> his right vnto him in theſe words; <hi>Sauing to all perſon and perſons, Bodies politique and their Succeſſors, all ſuch right, claime, title, intereſt, poſſeſsion, Rent-Charges,</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:16794:45"/>
               <hi>Annuities, Leaſes, Farmes, offices, Fees, Liueries and Liuings, Portions, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Commons, Synodies, Proxies, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profits, which any of them haue, claime, ought, may, or might haue had in or to the premiſſes, or to any part or parcell thereof, in ſuch like manner, forme, and condition, to all intents, respects, and purpoſes, as if this Act had neuer beene had, ne made, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words <hi>Saluo Iure</hi> (as one ſaith) <note place="margin">Bartol. ad l. ſi debitor. ff. Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus modis pigh. vel Hypolſ. ſol.</note> 
               <hi>verba ſunt magnae efficaciae;</hi> and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is giuen by <hi>Bartolus,</hi> becauſe <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatio conſeruat ius proteſtanti.</hi> And as they are words of great efficacie; ſo likewiſe are they of very large extent: For this word <hi>Ius, Ad perſonas, ad Res, ad actiones pertinet,</hi> ſaith the Emperour <hi>Iustinian.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuſtit. lib.</hi> 4.</note> And therefore when all right is ſaued and reſerued by the Act, it is manifeſt, That the Right of Action and Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie is reſerued as well as any other; For it were a vaine thing for the law, to giue a man Right to a thing, and not a Right of Action, to recouer it. Well
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16794:46"/>
then, the <hi>Statute</hi> ſaith <hi>vnto euery perſon, Bodies politique and their Succeſſors;</hi> All right and claime to any part or parcell of any lands, Parſonages appropriate, or other Hereditaments, Liuings, or profits comming to the King, by the diſſolution of the <hi>Manaſteries.</hi> A <hi>Vicar</hi> is a body politique, and had at the time of the Diſſolution, Right, Claime, and Action to ſo much of the Appropriate <hi>Parſonage,</hi> as would make a congruous and competent portion for his mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as hath been before declared. Therefore this right is reſerued and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to him and his ſucceſſors ſtill: And ſo ſaued to all intents and purpoſes, as if this Act had neuer been made. Had this Statute neuer been made, the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries</hi> had neuer finally bin diſſolued, had they continued, this Action had been good againſt them: and therefore is ſtill good againſt the <hi>Proprietary</hi> who now ſucceedeth in the Abbats place.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:16794:46"/>
at the time of the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> had a right of power and Iuriſdiction in himſelfe whenſoeuer the Abbat preſented a Clerke vnto him for inſtitution, not to admit him, vnleſſe the Abbat would firſt allot, lay out, and aſſigne a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient portion for his maintenance. If the Abbat had not made ſuch allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance within the time limited by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, the Biſhop had a right in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to collate the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icarage</hi> vpon the Preſentee, and to make a fit allowance for him, at his diſcretion, out of the fruits and profits of the Appropriation, by ſequeſtring them vnto his vſes. If the Abbat refuſed to obey, or preſumed to violate his ſequeſtration, the Biſhop had power to compell him by Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Cenſure, and Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the end wherof was impriſonment by the Secular armes, without Baile or Mainpriſe, vntill the order be obeyed. If the Abbat preſented not at all, the Ordinarie had right of Collation, as in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:16794:47"/>
Caſe of Lapſe and Deuolution: and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally hee had a right and power in himſelfe, to taxe the Benefices in fauour of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icars,</hi> as hath beene formerly prooued both by the Lawes, and alſo by the practiſe of thoſe times.</p>
            <p>This right the Biſhops had at the time of the <hi>Diſſolution;</hi> therefore this right is ſafe vnto him ſtill; and ſafe to all intents and purpoſes, as if this Acte had neuer beene had ne made. Had this Act neuer been made, the Abbats had ſtill continued, and vpon them hee might now exerciſe, as formerly he did, all that his power, right and Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Therefore hee may now proceede in like manner againſt the <hi>Proprietarie</hi> which holdeth the ſame in his poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at this day, and in no other manner, forme, ſtate and condition then the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat did: For the words are plaine, That what right ſoeuer hee might claime if this Statute had not bin made, the ſame he may claime ſtill notwithſtanding it is made.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:16794:47"/>
And it is to bee obſerued, that the Statute vſeth as generall words as the wit of man could poſſibly deuiſe, <hi>Sauing to all perſons, &amp;c. to all Bodies politique, &amp;c. All right, title, claime, interest, liuing, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profits, &amp;c.</hi> thereby to giue ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to euery man that might feare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preiudice to himſelfe from this Act. And therefore if the Biſhop ſhould ſay, My Iuriſdiction and my intereſt of Right in aſſigning a due portion vnto the <hi>Vicar</hi> at my diſcretion, is impeached, becauſe the <hi>Parſonage</hi> now goeth to the King, and from him to other Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The Statute anſwereth that, No: For all his right and intereſt is ſaued to him as if this Statute had neuer been made. If the <hi>Vicar</hi> ſhould ſay, That by the lawe heretofore hee had <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruam Portionem</hi> by way of <hi>Prouiſo</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and due vnto him: and that hee could ſue the Abbat before his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie for ſo much of the <hi>Parſonage</hi> as would ſerue to maintain him in a more
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:16794:48"/>
fitte and decent faſhion: But that now hee hath no Action againſt the King or any otherman. The Statute anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, That what title ſoeuer the <hi>Vicar,</hi> as a Body politique, had to any part or parcell of the Parſonage, the ſame is preſerued and ſaued to him ſtill, aſwell againſt the King, as againſt his grantee, in as ample maner as it was heretofore belonging to him againſt the Abbat. That whereas hee claimeth allowance out of the Rectorie, vnder the name of <hi>Portion,</hi> bee it certaine or vncertaine: Let him but looke the booke, and hee ſhall find, that the Parlament was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to reſerue all <hi>Portions</hi> in expreſſe termes, to any Body politique, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which could claime them, in ſuch manner and forme as hee might haue claimed it if this Satute had neuer been made.</p>
            <p>For it is manifeſt, that the meaning of the Parlament was not to hurt, or hinder any man, but onely to ſuppreſſe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:16794:48"/>
the <hi>Monkes,</hi> in that it was tender and carefull to reſerue to euery man his right, by what name or title ſoeuer he could claime it, <hi>Rents-Charges, Annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Fees, Penſions, Portions;</hi> and to the Biſhops or others claiming Epiſcopall Iuriſdiction, all <hi>Synodies, Proxies,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profits: So that as the wit of man could not deuiſe more generall termes to comprehend all mens rights; ſo the grauitie of a Parlament could not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to more particular wordes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe euery mans right, which it la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to preſerue. And as for the point of Iuriſdiction, the Parlament was ſo farre from deueſting the Biſhops of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part thereof, That it ſubmitted all exempt places of Monaſteries, or other priuiledged houſes to their Iuriſdiction. Much leſſe was it their meaning, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar</hi> of that ſmall meanes which the Law affoorded him, by quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling the Biſhop vpon this point of Iuriſdiction, rather then vpon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:16794:49"/>
Neither can I thinke, but that if any of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> high <hi>Court,</hi> whereunto no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vſeth to bee called, nothing is admitted, but the flower of wit, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and wiſedome ſhould now bee raiſed from the dead, and asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their meaning was, when they had ſaued vnto euery other man his right, onely to wrong the Biſhop? or when they had preſerued vnto euery other man his Claime to any part or parcell of thoſe Abbey-lands and Parſonages, onely to wring the <hi>Vicar,</hi> or to debarre him, not of that liberall allowance, which the law of God giueth him, but of that ſmall Remainder which the law of man hath left vnto him for his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, in regard of his dayly ſeruice at the Altar? He would anſwere, it was not their meaning; That the wordes of the Statute can beare no ſuch conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; That no Lawyer can wreſt the Statute to any ſuch ſenſe, vnleſſe hee firſt ſtraine his owne wit beyond ſenſe and reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:16794:49"/>
Neither can it be ſaid, That becauſe there is not in thoſe clauſes of <hi>reſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> any expreſſe mention made, either of the Biſhops iuriſdiction in this point, or of the Vicars portion in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, therefore it ought not now to be allowed.</p>
            <p>For the Statute maketh no mention at all of <hi>reparation</hi> of <hi>Chancels:</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Abbats receiuing the tithes, were out of them to keepe the <hi>Chancels</hi> in reparation; therefore the King alſo taking them into his hands, chargeth himſelfe and his Grantee with the ſame burden; for the leaſes of old times were wont to runne in this manner; <hi>Reddendo &amp; ſoluendo annuatim omnes &amp; ſingulas Procurationes, &amp;c. Ac etiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parando Cancellos earundem Eccleſiarum.</hi> Although in leaſes of latter times this clauſe is (as I take it) commonly left out. Likewiſe the Statute maketh no mention at all of any Curates wages to bee reſerued: yet doth the King in all
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:16794:50"/>
grants of Parſonages where there is no Vicar endowed, charge the Grantee with finding of a Curate. And the old leaſes were wont to runne in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; <hi>Soluendo annuatim omnes procuratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp;c. &amp; inueniendo Curatorem.</hi> But leaſes of later times, runne ſomewhat more ſparingly in this guiſe, <hi>yeelding, paying, and bearing all Proxies, Synodals, and ſtipends of Curats.</hi> In both theſe <hi>Caſes</hi> the King chargeth himſelfe with this burden, although there bee no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation thereof mentioned expreſſely in the Statute. But becauſe euery mans right was reſerued in the Statute, and the people of euery Pariſh had a right to haue Diuine Seruice ſaid vnto them, in conſideration of the tenth part of their yeerely profits which they giue in lieue of that, and of none other thing, therefore the King chargeth himſelfe with the finding of one that ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this duty to them. And becauſe ſuch a one muſt haue a mainetenance,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:16794:50"/>
therefore hee chargeth himſelfe or his Grantee with paying a ſtipend alſo. This he doth <hi>non ex gratia, ſed ex debito:</hi> And becauſe the Abbats, from whom he had thoſe Parſonages, were before the diſſolution charged with the ſame. Whence it followeth, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there be no expreſſe mention made in the Statute, of the iuriſdiction of the Biſhop in this point, and of the Vicars portion in particular: yet are they vnderſtood to be reſerued, becauſe they are alſo compriſed in the generall, as all others are.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, the <hi>Statutes</hi> of either kingdome which concerne this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, beare this colour in the face. <hi>That the Priors, Abbats, and other religious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, with the aſſent, and conſent of their ſeuerall Couents, and in writing vnder their Common Seale, gaue vp all their lands, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Parſonages appropriate, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icarages into the Kings hands.</hi> Vpon which <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render</hi> of theirs, the King was enabled
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:16794:51"/>
to haue, enioy, and poſſeſſe the ſame <hi>in ſuch manner and forme, &amp;c.</hi> Now it is manifeſt, that by vertue of their <hi>Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> nothing could come vnto the kings hand, but that which was theirs: And it is as manifeſt, that the right of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and the claime of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar,</hi> were not in the <hi>Abbat</hi> or <hi>Prior;</hi> and therefore cannot be intended to paſſe vnto the King by any Act of theirs. For <hi>Quod meum eſt ſine facto meo à me tranferri non poteſt:</hi> that which is mine cannot paſſe from mee, but by ſome Act of mine. Laſtly, ſome men are of opinion, that this courſe cannot be taken for the benefit of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat his right and action, if any he had before, is now extinct and loſt, becauſe the Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation comming to the Kings hand, the nature of the thing it ſelfe is altered, and made a Lay Fee: But they may bee pleaſed to be informed, that the nature of thoſe things continueth ſtill the ſame, and is not changed. For in the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:16794:51"/>
               <hi>Statute</hi> of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. It is expreſly ſaied, That the King ſhall hold thoſe lands of <hi>Chantries, Colledges,</hi> and <hi>free Chappels,</hi> in as large and ample <hi>manner and forme as the Prieſts hell them, &amp;c. and in their natures and qualities:</hi> So then, though the King now holdeth them to a different end and vſe, yet hee holdeth them in the ſame nature which they had before. And what I pray you can the nature of theſe and ſuch like things, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt <hi>in Iure</hi> be, but the manner, forme, ſtate, and condition, wherein they are poſſeſſed? Now it hath beene former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared, that they are ſtill held in the ſame manner, forme, ſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, wherein they were held before: therefore it followeth, that they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtill in the ſame nature; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that their <hi>Nature</hi> is not altered or changed. Moreouer, it is a Rule in <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> that <hi>Formadat nomen &amp; eſſe,</hi> the forme of euery thing giueth it name and nature; nay, rather it is the very
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:16794:52"/>
nature and eſſence of the thing it ſelfe; as for example. The reaſonable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall ſoule of a man is his forme: And therefore the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſay, That <hi>Anima eſt quiſque:</hi> it is the ſoule that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth euery man to be what he is, in his proper nature, and is the man it ſelfe: whence it followeth, That becauſe the <hi>Proprietaries</hi> hold the <hi>Benefices</hi> in the ſame forme in which the <hi>Abbats</hi> held them, therefore they hold them in the ſame nature alſo; and conſequently, their nature remaineth, and is not alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And why ſhould we thinke, that the nature of theſe things is altered ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the name, ſeeing that the forme which giueth both alike, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth ſtill the ſame? Looke the <hi>ſtatutes,</hi> and you ſhall euer finde them called by the ſame names which they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: <hi>Benefices, Rectories, Parſonages, Appropriations, Tithes, Church-duties,</hi> and the like. But by the name of Lay fees or Chattels, you ſhall neuer finde them
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:16794:52"/>
mentioned in the <hi>Statutes.</hi> And to ſhew yet further, that in the opinion of that very Parlament, which made the Acts of <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> as alſo in conſtruction of Law, it was generally vnderſtood, That the nature of theſe Appropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Tithes remained ſtill the ſame, without change or alteration; It may pleaſe them to conſider, That when the <hi>Monaſteries</hi> were all diſſolued, and laid waſt, and the Impropriations ſold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into Lay-mens hands: yet were the Tithes vnto them, like Nuts caſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to little children, which could not cracke them: Neither had thoſe Laie men any meanes, or Action to recouer them: And therefore by the <hi>Statute</hi> of 32. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Lay men were enabled to ſue for Tithes in the <hi>Eccleſiasticall Court.</hi> By which it plainely appeareth, that theſe Tithes retaine ſtill the nature of Eccleſiaſtical duties and goods proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonging to the <hi>Church;</hi> elſe why ſhould the <hi>Ordinarie</hi> hold plea of them
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:16794:53"/>
betweene Lay men more then of other Chattels? And if they had altered their nature, and of Tithes had beene made Chattels or lay Fees, why ſhould they not haue beene recouered by action of debt, or otherwiſe at the <hi>Common Law,</hi> without hauing recourſe at all to the Court <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> Therefore the nature and qualitie of theſe Appropriations and Tithes is not altered, by comming into lay mens hands, no more then a peece of Coine is changed, when it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from one hand to the other.</p>
            <p>From all which I conclude, That what right ſoeuer the <hi>Biſhop</hi> had to his Iuriſdiction, the Pariſh to haue a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the Miniſter to haue allowance before the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of theſe <hi>Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and making of the fore recited <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> the ſame they and euery of them haue at this day notwithſtanding thoſe <hi>Statutes;</hi> and the rather for them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they help to ſaue that Right, both of Iuriſdiction to the one, &amp; of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:16794:53"/>
to the other, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might ſeeme to haue beene loſt in both.</p>
            <p>This then I take to be cleare in Law, That whereſoeuer a Vicar is to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, there alſo a competent main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is to bee allowed. But then there remaineth yet a doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all Churches in generall which heretofore belonged to the Monkes, are neceſſarily to be ſerued with perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Vicars, or may be ſupplied with Stipendarie Curates; a doubt of too great difficultie to be diſſembled, and of too great conſequence to be negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in that Kingdom: becauſe all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietaries there, deſire to gaine this point vpon the Biſhops, and ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend more colourable reaſon for it, then others doe.</p>
            <p>For the better clearing of this doubt, it is to be obſerued, That the Parſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were heretofore either granted to the Monkes, <hi>In proprios <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus,</hi> from
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:16794:54"/>
whence they haue their name of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations; or elſe they were vnited to their Tables, &amp; are therefore called <hi>Menſalia</hi> in the Law. Concerning the nature and qualitie of the former. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cent. ad c. pastoralis: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra de priuileg. nu.</hi> 1.</note> ſayth, that, <hi>Per haec verba (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedimus tibi Eccleſiam in proprios vſus) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit concedere, quod administrationem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat Eccleſiae: Et quod retento bono statu Eccleſiae ſuperfluos tantum reditus in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prios vſus conuertat: Debet enim Eccleſiam ſibi conceſſam in primo ſtatu retinere.</hi> And <hi>Panormitan</hi> in his Commentaries vpon the Chapter <hi>De Monachis. Tit. de Praeben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> alledging the ſame words of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius,</hi> addeth further, <hi>Habent etiam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentationem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ad c. de M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis extra de Praebend.</note> 
               <hi>Rectoris ex tali conceſsione.</hi> If then the Monkes had by vertue of ſuch Grant, onely the preſentation, it is manifeſt, that the Inſtitution was ſtill reſerued to the Biſhop. And that in this caſe the Vicar ought to be perpetuall, and to receiue Canonicall Inſtitution from the Ordinarie, appeareth by all
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:16794:54"/>
thoſe Canons which I haue formerly alledged for proofe of the Vicars por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So doeth it alſo, and more plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by a certaine Decretall of <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. where he ſaith, <hi>Presbyteri qui per Monachos in earum Eccleſiis praeſentantur</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. de capell. monachorum: in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o.</note> 
               <hi>Epiſcopis, &amp; inſtituuntur ab ipſis, cum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant eſſe perpetui, conſuetudine vel Statuto quouis in contrarium non obſtante, &amp;c</hi> And the Pope was wont in his Grants of Appropriatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alwaies to adde a clauſe of reſeruation of maintenance, <hi>Vicarijs Canonicè inſtituendis.</hi> By which it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, That all Appropriations made <hi>Quoad temporalia,</hi> or <hi>in proprios vſus,</hi> ought to haue a Perpetuall Vicar, which is to receiue his Canonicall Inſtitution in forme of Law, from the Ordinarie. Of this ſort are almoſt all the Appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Kingdome which haue lighted into my hand: and thus they paſſe. <hi>Salua ſuſtentatione Vicariorum: ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo iure Epiſcopi: in vſus ſuos proprios con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertant.</hi> And many times, as namely in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:16794:55"/>
an Appropriation which I haue ſeene of the Rectory of <hi>Ballrouthery,</hi> made by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi> to the Prior and Couent of <hi>Kilbixi,</hi> together with the erection of the Vicarage and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſaued to the Vicar, this right of Inſtitution is reſerued by expreſſe termes to the Biſhop, and the Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation onely left vnto the Prior; ſo that this kinde of Appropriation cannot warrant the Proprietaries to collate the Curateſhip as now they doe, and ſend their Curate for a Licence to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. But they are to preſent, and the Biſhop is of right to grant him In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, as well for the title of the Benefice, as for the Cure of ſoules: And no marueile: For beſides that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour in the beginning taught vs, <hi>That an hired ſhepheard was neuer profitable for the ſheepe;</hi> the Canons alſo of the olde Church ordained in this manner, <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipimus etiam, ne Conductitijs Presbyteris</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>s. vlt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eccleſiae committantur:</hi> A precept worthy
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:16794:55"/>
to be written in letters of gold ouer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Church doore, as a <hi>Charme,</hi> to keep out the deſtroyer. But to let paſſe the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and cuſtoms of former ages in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine countreys, &amp; to make it yet more plaine, That euen within this kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Biſhops euer claimed, and euer had this right of <hi>Inſtitution</hi> to all ſuch Churches as the Monkes helde <hi>in proprios vſus:</hi> and thereupon laid out reaſonable allowances for the Vicar. I haue ſeene an ancient <hi>Bull</hi> of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, whom I noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to haue beene the firſt that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe againſt the auarice of the Monkes in this kinde. To him certaine Monkes of this Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> made their complaint againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops for troubling them in this point: and craued a priuiledge againſt their authoritie for the time to come; which hee graunted: and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his religious Graunt in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Nos itaque veſtris ſupplicationibus</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:16794:56"/>
               <hi>inclinati, vt ſicut hactenus, ſic &amp; in poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Regiſtr. Sancti T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minghans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dublin.</note> 
               <hi>poſsitis in dictis Eccleſiis, per huiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Canonicos &amp; Capellanos veſtros fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere deſeruiri, nec vobis inuitis taxari va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leant Vicariae, ſeu Vicarij perpetui inſtitui in ijſae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, auctoritate Apoſtolica indulgemus, &amp;c. Si quis autem contra attemptare praeſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſerit, indignationem Omnipotentis Dei, &amp; Beatorum Petri &amp; Pauli Apoſtolorum eius ſe nouerit incurſurum, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which it is plaine and euident, That as the Proprietaries of theſe dayes doe; ſo did their predeceſſors and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors the <hi>Monkes,</hi> firſt in ſtipendarie <hi>Curates:</hi> and make them the leaſt allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that poſſiblie they could: But when the Biſhops challenged their right, and began to know themſelues in their places, the <hi>Monkes</hi> then fledde, not to the ſanctuary of the Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was againſt them, neither ſtood they vpon their cuſtome, which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not grounded vpon reaſon) was not able to protect them: but hauing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:16794:56"/>
no other refuge, ſought to the <hi>Pope</hi> for a priuiledge, in ſtead of a pardon, for ſuch abuſes committed already, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to bee committed. A ſtrange Caſe, That the <hi>Vicar</hi> of CHRIST here on earth, ſhould grant ſo lewd a priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. But this euer was, and ſtil is, the practiſe and policie of that Sea, To make ſtrict, and, many times, good lawes, and then to grant large and lewd <hi>Dispenſations;</hi> thereby to ſatiate (if it were poſſible) her inſatiable auarice. But to returne vnto our purpoſe: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this, nor any other like priuiledge could, before the <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> free the <hi>Monkes,</hi> nor can at this time exempt the Proprietaries their ſucceſſors from the Iuriſdiction and power of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> in that behalfe. For long after the dayes of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, Clement the fift, ſeeing the deſolation which grew dayly vpon the Church by reaſon of ſuch abuſes of the <hi>Monkes,</hi> eſpecially in that they ſerued their Cures by their
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:16794:57"/>
               <hi>Chapleins</hi> and ſtipendary <hi>Curates,</hi> made the Decree which I mentioned before, thereby enioyning the <hi>Monkes</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their Clerkes vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Ordinarie, from him to receiue <hi>Canonicall instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> All which hee commandeth to be obſerued: <hi>Non obſtantibus exemptionibus, aut alijs quibuſlibet priuilegijs, conſuetudini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vel Statutis. Quae circa praemiſſa vel eorum aliquod Religioſis ipſis in nullo volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſuffragari.</hi> This hee decreed, not fearing the indignation of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> which by the curſe of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the third hee was to incurre: but perſwading himſelfe (as well he might) that God would neuer bee offended with him for cancelling a priuiledge which tended ſo directly to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of his worſhip and ſeruice, and to the deſtruction of his Church here on earth: wherefore if any Proprietarie would at this day plead the like priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge granted to <hi>Monkes</hi> from whome hee deriues his Title, hee muſt ſhew it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:16794:57"/>
granted ſince the time of <hi>Clement</hi> the fift, and with a <hi>Non obſtante</hi> to that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of his, otherwiſe the <hi>Clementine</hi> reacheth to them of after date, aſwell as to the former: neither can they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, that they haue vſed ſo to doe time out of minde, and beyond the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of man; for ſo had thoſe <hi>Monkes,</hi> and yet wanted a priuiledge to protect them: and the <hi>Clementine</hi> runneth with a <hi>Non obſtante</hi> of any cuſtome or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription: whence I conclude, That all Proprietaries which at this day holde Churches which were anciently giuen <hi>in proprios vſus</hi> to the <hi>Monkes,</hi> may not now, as they doe, nominate their <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,</hi> and ſend them to the <hi>Ordinarie</hi> for a licence: but muſt as <hi>Patrons,</hi> preſent their Clerkes vnto him, and hee (if they bee worthy) muſt giue them Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Inſtitution, and make them perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>Vicars</hi> or Rectors of the Church, with cure of ſoules: For ſuch was the ſtate of the Church before the Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:16794:58"/>
made, and ſuch it muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
            <p>But the greater doubt is of thoſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices which were giuen <hi>ad Menſam Monachorum.</hi> Theſe Grants were made by way of Vnion, and paſſe vnder diuers formes: ſometime by theſe words <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedimus pleno iure:</hi> ſometimes <hi>vtroque iure:</hi> ſometimes <hi>pleno iure, tam in ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus quam in temporalibus.</hi> The proper effect of all which Grants ſeemeth to bee, That theſe Benefices need no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Vicar, but may bee ſerued by a Stipendarie Curate. For firſt theſe are excepted from the generall, where it is <note place="margin">C cum &amp; plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare: extra de priuilegij. C. in Latera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od.</note> ſaid, <hi>In Eccleſiis vero ſuis, quae ad eos pleno iure non pertinent, inſtituendos Presbyteros Epiſcopis repraeſentent.</hi> By which it is implyed, that if they held them <hi>pleno iure,</hi> they could not bee compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to preſent. And in another place it is ſaid, <hi>Praemiſſa vero intelligimus de bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficijs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> praelato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>quae non ſunt de menſa Praelatorum ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum, ſed ſpeciales Rectores habere conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt:</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:16794:58"/>
by which it appeareth, that they had no certaine <hi>Rector</hi> nor perpetuall <hi>Vicar;</hi> but were ſerued by a Chaplaine. And the <hi>Clementine,</hi> in the Title <hi>De ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſu Praelatorum,</hi> blameth the Biſhops for troubling the <hi>Monkes</hi> in this point, <note place="margin">De exeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lato. in Clement.</note> as if vpon the death of their Stipendary <hi>Curates</hi> the Benefices had fallen voide, <hi>Quanquam ipſae per hoc Eccleſiae in veritate non vacent,</hi> ſaith the Law. The ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Gloſſe vpon this place is famous, and <note place="margin">Gloſſ. ib.</note> all after-writers referre themſelues vnto it: where the queſtion being put, What were thoſe Churches which might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly bee ſayd to bee <hi>De menſâ Praelato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum?</hi> The anſwere is, <hi>Quod illae, quae ſunt menſis eorum vnitae, in tantum quod Rectorem, vell vicarium perpetuum non habeant, alium quam illum cui facta est annexio.</hi> And the Doctours of the Audience in <hi>Rome,</hi> vpon a caſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, make this difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene an Appropriation and an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Cum Eccleſia conceditur alicui Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterio</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:16794:59"/>
               <hi>pleno iure in temporalibus, tunc Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rola in nouis.</note> 
               <hi>debent inſtituere Vicarium perpetuum: vbi vero vaitur menſae Epiſcopali, vel Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batiali, &amp; ſpectant ad illam pleno iure tam in ſpiritualibus, quam in temporalibus, tunc ponetur in ea Presbyter temporalis, ad nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum remouibilis, ad exercitium Curae, quae principaliter reſidet in eo, cuius menſae eſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita</hi> And <hi>Rebuffus</hi> following the ſame ſteppes, and ſpeaking of a graunt of a Benefice, made by theſe words, <hi>pleno iure, vel vtroque iure,</hi> addeth this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. <hi>Per hoc intelligitur quod tam its</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rebuff. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grua portio.</note> 
               <hi>temporalibus, quam in ſpiritualibus iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem habent, &amp; in ijs Eccleſis constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur, Vicarii temporales ad nutum reuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles, quibus non prouidetur de congrua por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi> And laſtly <hi>Ranchinus,</hi> in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations vpon <hi>Guido Papa. Deciſione</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ranchinus ad Guid. Papa.</hi> 154.</note> 154. ſaith that, <hi>Illae Eccleſiae dicuntur de menſa quae ſunt ita vnitae, quod non habeant Vicarium perpetuum.</hi> From all which it may be gathered, That thoſe Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, who now hold Parſonages,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:16794:59"/>
which were heeretofore vnited to the Tables of the <hi>Monkes;</hi> becauſe they are to hold them in the ſame manner, forme, and condition, as the <hi>Monkes</hi> did, cannot now bee forced to preſent their Clerks to the Ordinary for inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, no more then the <hi>Monkes</hi> could heretofore; but are onely to ſend him for a licence as now they doe. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all which, I take the law to be otherwiſe, as the caſe now ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: For the Monaſteries might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede heeretofore, ſerue the Cure in Churches belonging to their Table, by a temporary Curate, if that Curate were a <hi>Monke,</hi> as commonly hee was: or if there were no Pariſh belonging to the Church, but if the Church were Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall, and the Curate ſecular, then hee was to receiue inſtitution from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, as perpetuall Vicar, and to haue a competent allowance out of the fruits of the Benefice, as other Vicars had. And therefore <hi>Zabarella,</hi> hauing hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:16794:60"/>
this point, giueth this caueate in the end. <hi>Sed nota &amp; ſigna mente quod</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zabarel. ad lit. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. neglige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Traeiat</note> 
               <hi>hoc ita procedit ſi Abbas ibi collocat vnum de ſuis Monachis, ſecus ſi ſaecularem; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent enim Beneficia eſſe perpetua; &amp; hoc non reperitur eſſe permiſſum in ſaecularibus.</hi> Wherefore ſeeing that now all thoſe Churches are parochiall, and the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates ſecular, it followeth, That the Proprietaries are now to preſent their Clerkes, as their Anceſtors the Abbats were bound to doe in the like caſe: for, <hi>Res redijt in eum caſum, vnde incipere non potuit:</hi> There are at this time with vs no <hi>Monkes</hi> in being: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Vicar muſt now of neceſſity be ſecular; and beeing ſecular hee muſt be alſo preſentatiue and perpetuall; for ſo the law ordaineth. And it is farther to be obſerued, That thoſe very <hi>Monks,</hi> could not ſerue the Cure in a Church remote from the Abbey. For the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran</hi> Councell, forbad <hi>Monkes</hi> to bee appointed and placed, as Curates in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:16794:60"/>
Churches about the Countrey: And <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the third ordained, that <hi>In Eccleſiis vbi Monachi habitant, populus per monachum non regatur.</hi> So that neither as Curate in Churches remote, neither yet as Rector, in the very Pariſh wher they dwelt, could a <hi>Monke</hi> be imployed: onely in thoſe Churches which were neere adioyning to their Monaſteries, where they might ſing Maſſe in the morning, and returne to their <hi>Dorter</hi> at night, they were permitted to ſerue; and theſe were commonly vnited to their Table, and none other. And this is the cauſe why <hi>Archidiaconus,</hi> a Father amongſt the <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, ſi vicina eſt, regitur per Priorem &amp; capitulum: ſi vero remota eſt imponetur ei cenſus, &amp; ponetur in ea Presbyter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuus.</hi> For in proceſſe of time, the <hi>Monkes</hi> finding that theſe vnions to <note place="margin">Archidiacon. ad C. cum ſingulis de prebend. &amp; dignit. in ſexto</note> their Table, were more priuiledged in this point, then others, procured Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices farre diſtant alſo, to bee vnited to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:16794:61"/>
their Tables: And therefore the Popes of later times, in granting or confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming theſe vnions, were wont to make the like reſeruation, as in other ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Appropriations, as <hi>Rebuffus</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And againe, in ordinary Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations, if the Benefices lay neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Abbeies, the Biſhop was wont to winke at it, and to ſuffer them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Cure by ſome one of their <hi>Monkes,</hi> or other ſtipendary Curates, as if they had beene <hi>menſall.</hi> I mentioned before a certaine contention, which fell betweene <hi>Richard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Meath</hi> and certaine <hi>Monkes;</hi> vpon whoſe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated Benefices, he placed perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Vicars of his owne authority, and made them allowances at his owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion: yet did he not vſe this right and power on all, but onely vpon twelue; yeelding this reaſon of his act, Becauſe thoſe twelue were farre off from the Abbey, and lay neere the high way, where it was neceſſary that ſome kept
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:16794:61"/>
reſidence for the receiuing of Pilgrims and ſtrangers, that were to paſſe that way: The reſt hee forbare to taxe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they lay neere vnto ſome Grange of the Abbey: And therefore if any came thither for hoſpitalitie, they might aſwell repaire vnto the Grange it ſelfe, there to bee receiued: which cauſe of toleration (how good or bad ſoeuer it were) now ceaſeth in our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietaries, becauſe they will not make their houſes Innes for trauellers as the Abbats did: wherefore as they can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend no better right then the Abbats had, ſo they may not in diſcretion challenge the like ſufferance of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop as they found.</p>
            <p>To conclude, the ſumme of all is this. In Benefices giuen to the vſe of the Monkes, which are properly called Appropriations, or Impropriations, the Ordinarie now is, and euer was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction to ordaine a <hi>Perpetuall Vicar</hi> with <hi>Cure of ſoules:</hi> And to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:16794:62"/>
the Proprietarie to a competent and conuenient allowance out of the fruits of the Benefice for his mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: And in thoſe <hi>Menſall</hi> Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which were vnited to their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the Ordinarie is (as the ſtate of things now ſtandeth) to doe the like: So that in all, and all maner of Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as well Menſall as other, heretofore belonging to thoſe Abbeys or other Religious Houſes, and which are now in the hands of the Proprietaries with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Kingdome, theſe mercenarie and ſeruing creatures, theſe ſtipendarie Curats are by courſe of Law to be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; and in their roomes <hi>Perpetuall Vicars</hi> or <hi>Rectors,</hi> with ſufficiencie of meanes to be ordained.</p>
            <p>Sufficiencie of meanes I ſay; For it was long ſince obſerued, That beggerly Poets neuer made good Verſes; for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie is a heauie burden, and the feare thereof worketh as violently vpon the wit and ſpirit of a man, as any terrour
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:16794:62"/>
doeth, and is therefore reckoned by the Orator, <hi>inter grauiſsima vitae onera.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tullie. de ſene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu.</note> And it is certaine, that there is no one thing which doeth more depreſſe and keepe downe the minde and riſing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a man, from aſpiring to any high inuention or conceit of learning, then that doeth:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Nam ſi Virgilio puer &amp; tolerabile deeſſet <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>enalis.</note> Hoſpitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, caderent omnes à crinib Hydrae: Surda nihil caneret graue buccina:—</q> ſayth the <hi>Satyriſt.</hi> His meaning is, that <hi>Virgil</hi> himſelfe could neuer haue deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the ſlaughter of <hi>Turnus,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats of <hi>Aeneas,</hi> the fury of <hi>Amata,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like Arguments, with that high conceit and ſtraine of wit, and with ſuch loftineſſe of ſtile as hee hath done, had his mind beene troubled and diſtracted with want of neceſſaries for food, raiment, houſe-rent, and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance at home: Neither may we hope for better of a Preacher, if the like weight of want and pouertie lie vpon
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:16794:63"/>
him: and therefore it is requiſite, that a ſufficient maintenance be prouided for him, for ſo the law requireth.</p>
            <p>But then there remaineth a great and difficult queſtion, <hi>What is ſufficient for this Vicars maintenance?</hi> For mine owne part, I may not preſume to preſcribe what is enough or ſufficient in this caſe, becauſe the Law leaueth it to the diſcretion of the Biſhop, who muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe of many particulars, and frame his cenſure according to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate motions of his owne well diſpoſed mind; nay, I may well ſay as a learned <hi>Canoniſt</hi> hath ſaid already, <hi>De re ista non potest certa tradi doctrina.</hi> Onely we muſt beware, that whileſt we reckon all too little for our ſelues, we thinke not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing enough for the Miniſter of the Church. <hi>Zabarella</hi> vpon this queſtion ſaith, <hi>Quod ſola ſustentatio non ſufficiet, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt namque eſſe talis, quod non periret fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; tamen non eſſet congrua, ſicut eſſe debet in victu &amp; veſtitu, &amp; alijs congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entibus.</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:16794:63"/>
And as another Writer ſaieth, <hi>Vicarijs de hac portione congrue prouidebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; nec cogentur veſci fabis, &amp; alijs vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus cibarijs ſicut Ruſtici.</hi> Firſt, therefore in this Aſsignation of his portion, there muſt be care taken, that hee may haue enough for his food and rayment in a decent &amp; conuenient maner. Secondly, reſpect is to be had vnto his family. <hi>Non enim ſufficiens dicitur Beneficium, niſi ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiens fit habenti, &amp; perſonis ſibi neceſsarijs.</hi> But who are theſe? and how many ſhal he be allowed to keepe? No man I thinke will allow him leſſe then a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant or two to attend vpon him. <hi>Non enim debet ſibi coquere,</hi> ſaith one. But this is not all: for the law of God permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and the Lawes of this kingdome haue made it free for Miniſters to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as well as others, conſidering well, That the eſtate it ſelfe is honorable in al men alike: and that they conſiſting of fleſh and blood as others doe, haue like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their deſires vpon them as others haue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:16794:64"/>
It is reaſon therefore, that ſince the law permitteth them to marry, the law ſhould alſo prouide them a mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, for the eaſier bearing of ſuch a burthen, elſe is their condition more miſerable then any other: for worke they may not, which heretofore they might; and to begge they are aſhamed. Merchandize they cannot, which yet the <hi>Ciuile Law</hi> permitteth; and not to prouide for their family, were a fault worſe then Infidelitie: and therefore vnleſſe meanes be allowed for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of thoſe, as well as of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, it had beene better for them if they had ſtill remained as they were. Thirdly, regard muſt be had vnto hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitie: for it hath euer bin thought fit, that the Miniſter ſhould be enabled to releeue the poore, to feed the hungry, &amp; to receiue a ſtranger as he trauaileth on the way: a thing more conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this kingdome then in the other of <hi>England,</hi> for our want of <hi>Innes;</hi> and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:16794:64"/>
becauſe the Countrey is of cuſtome more harborous to paſſengers, if neede requireth. And laſtly, to omit all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his perſon, as Nobilitie, degree, deſert, age, and ſuch like, which are not forgotten in other <hi>Countries,</hi> when the poore <hi>Vicars</hi> portion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in queſtion, before the <hi>Ordinarie</hi> or other <hi>Iudge, Conſiderabitur in ijs hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas, vt bonoretur in ijs officium Sacerdotale,</hi> ſaith a <hi>Canonist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome man will ſay, that this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is long ſince anſwered, and the doubt determined by Act of Parlament here in <hi>Ireland.</hi> It is true, that in the 33. yeere of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, there paſſed here an Act; wherein it was contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That whereas diuers Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> were heretofore appropried to Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and other religious houſes, now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, wherein <hi>Diuine Seruice</hi> was done, maintained, and kept, and the Cure ſerued by religious perſons of the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:16794:65"/>
ſaid religious houſes, &amp;c. Therefore there ſhould be an able man appointed for that purpoſe in euery Pariſh-Church. In conſideration whereof, and to the intent aforeſaid, it ſhould be enacted, That Sir <hi>Anthonie Saintleger,</hi> Lord Deputie of <hi>Ireland, I. A.</hi> Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the kingdome, <hi>W. B.</hi> Vicetreaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and <hi>S. A.</hi> Chiefe <hi>Iustice,</hi> with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry others there named, or any ſixe of them, the foure officers aboue named to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> might and ſhould erect and incorporate one <hi>Vicarage</hi> of one <hi>Vicar,</hi> in euery of the ſaid Pariſhes, as they ſhould think conuenient, which ſhould haue ſucceſſion of the ſame for euer, to be preſented by the Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie, bee inſtituted by the <hi>Ordinarie,</hi> &amp;c. And that the ſaid Sir <hi>Anthonie</hi> and the reſt might and ſhould aſſigne and appoint vnto euery ſuch <hi>Vicar,</hi> ſuch conuenient portions of Tithes alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, and oblations of the poſſeſſions comming to the King by reaſon of the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:16794:65"/>
ſaid diſſolution, for the maintenance of <hi>Diuine</hi> ſeruice, and keeping of <hi>Hospita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> &amp;c. Prouided alwaies, that ſuch Aſſignation did not exceed the yearely valew of 13. pounds ſixe ſhillings and eight pence: and reſeruing to the King the twentieth part out of euery ſuch <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carage,</hi> and the <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Act indeede was made, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth of record in the <hi>Rolles</hi> of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but it neuer tooke effect. But be it that it were ſtil of force, what proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath the ſumme limited, with the ends for which it is appointed? or what maintenance is ten pounds ſterling at the vtmoſt for a Miniſter, to liue in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of a Miniſter withall? to find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? to maintaine his wife and children while he is aliue, to prouide for them after his death, to pay ſeruants wages; and ouer and aboue all this, to keepe hoſpitality, which the <hi>Statute</hi> intendeth and commandeth to be kept?</p>
            <p>It may be, that in thoſe daies it was
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:16794:66"/>
enough: but what is it at this preſent time? Had this Statute taken his effect, yet had it beene reaſon, that at this time the <hi>Vicars</hi> ſhould haue claimed a new taxation, ſeeing that the rates of all things are now raiſed to a higher price: Moreouer, it is apparant, that although <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight tooke away the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and ſuppreſſed the vſurped ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the Pope in his Dominions: yet hee reformed not Religion, and therefore their oblations and alterages, maſſe monies, and ſuch like fees (which were no doubt the greateſt part of the poore Vicars maintenance, and yet was neuer reckoned in his portion) remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all his daies: Seeing therefore that theſe are now grow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n into diſuſance, reaſon good that their allowance bee made good againe, and increaſed ſome other way. In the ſame Parliament, there was order taken for the hire of Slaters and other workemen by the day: and it is ordained that their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:16794:66"/>
ſhould bee increaſed from time to time, according to the prices of corne and other victualls: there is now no Carpenter or Slater heere, which will take leſſe then ſixteene pence <hi>per diem,</hi> for himſelfe, and twelue pence for his man, which amounteth to vpwards of thirtie pounds <hi>per ann.</hi> What reaſon therefore that the poore Miniſter, who ought to be <hi>honorabilis in populo,</hi> ſhould be held to the old taxation of twenty Markes <hi>Iriſh</hi> by the yeere at the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, which commeth not to eight pence <hi>per diem,</hi> for the maintenance of himſelfe and all his family? But the poore Vicars lot is not ſo good as to haue the allowance the Statute ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of. Our horſe-boies wages are not great; would God our Vicars were no worſe. Our horſe-boies haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly forty ſhillings wages, beſides meat, drinke and lodging, and foure paire of Broagues <hi>per ann.</hi> How la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable then is that which hath of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:16794:67"/>
late beene diſcouered, That through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Prouince of <hi>Connaught,</hi> and in ſundry other Dioceſſes of this Kingdome, the Vicarages, for the moſt part, are vnder forty, and many of them not aboue fifteene ſhillings ſterling, towards all charges, by the yeere? But to conclude this point: If any man thinke that twentie nobles or ten pounds ſterling, according to this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, be at this day a ſufficient and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable maintenance for a learned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Church, and Preacher of Gods word, to maintaine himſelfe, his wife, children, and family, and to keepe hoſpitality withall; and no reaſon will perſwade him to the contrary, I for my part will not bee contentious, nor vſe farther argument againſt him; onely I wiſh him more experience; and that (ſauing my charity) hee himſelfe, his wife, children, and family, might liue but one moneth according to that rate, and afterwards hee bee asked what hee
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:16794:67"/>
thought of the ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of ſuch allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Neither yet is this the <hi>nihil vltra,</hi> of our miſery, for euen vnto this day, as if the ghoſts of thoſe <hi>Monkes</hi> did ſtill walke and haunt vs, Eccleſiaſticall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings of all ſorts are continually taken from the Church, vnder colour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celements, and as if in old time, they had belonged to their houſes; In ſo much, that in one ſmall Dioces, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Elfin,</hi> twenty fiue Vicarages, fiue Rectories, and two Prebends, are found to haue beene reft from the Church by this occaſion; all which did anciently ſtand charged in the Kings bookes, with firſt fruits and twentieth part: An infallible argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſince the diſſolution, they haue beene in the proper vſe, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poſſeſſion of the Church; neither doe other Dioceſſe want their part in this calamity. And to adde to our griefe, his <hi>ſacred Name</hi> is heerein euer vſed; who of all men mortall would
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:16794:68"/>
moſt abhorre it. For hee that of his Princely bounty, and Chriſtian deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath of his owne, giuen wellnigh three hundred thouſand acres of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall good land, to the reuerend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, dignitaries, and Pariſh Churches, of the North of that Kingdome, would not he much more reſtore the tithes to the poore Vicars of other parts, if it may appeare that of right they belong vnto them? doth King <hi>Iames</hi> rule his ſubiects by one law, and himſelfe by another? or haue wee not yet proofe enough of his well willing to the Church? This then is an euill, which cannot be healed, but by that myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and medicinable hand of the King himſelfe: A hand, which often hath wrought, and daily doth worke greater miracles, and cure more running ſores then this, in the body of the Church and Common wealth; and will not leaue this vntoucht, if euer it happen to be brought vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:16794:68"/>
But to leaue what we haue not, and to returne to what we haue; I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſaid, and endeauoured to prooue, that the Biſhop is the man authoriſed by law, to aſſigne the Vicars portion: wherein, I am not ignorant, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men may happily draw my diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into queſtion, and condemne my iudgement, in labouring thus earneſtly to reuiue the memory of an old diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and almoſt forgotten point of law; for what if all were granted to be law that hath beene ſaid? what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit is the Church like to reape thereby, ſeeing that the execution thereof belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth onely to the Biſhops? weake men God wot, ſome will ſay, for the moſt part, in this Kingdome, to hold that they haue, but altogether vnable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer what they had: <hi>Medice cura te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum.</hi> Their Lordſhips ſhould doe well to recouer their owne rights firſt; and then wee ſhould haue ſome hope that they would be able to preuaile for the Vicars alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:16794:69"/>
True indeede: the execution of this law belongeth peculiarly to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: but it is as true, that in this their long default, it doth now as properly belong to the King: For there is no doubt, but that before thoſe Acts of <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> as ſupreame Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie pretended, made all thoſe Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and Canons which before are mentioned for the erection of <hi>Vicara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and maintenance of the <hi>Vicars;</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of which were directed to ſundry of our owne Biſhops in <hi>England:</hi> and they, by the toleration of the King, put them in execution from time to time, and were euer iuſtified in their doings, by the Reuerend Iudges of the land. If then the Souereigne power in theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and both the making and execution of theſe lawes did heretofore belong vnto the Pope; then is it manifeſt, that the ſame at this day doth immediatly belong vnto the King, vpon whom by way of <hi>Restitution,</hi> the Parliament hath
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:16794:69"/>
ſeated all the power which the <hi>Pope</hi> then vſurped, in lawes not repugnant to the word of God, and Statutes of the Kingdome. Wherefore if the Biſhop cannot, yet the King can doe them right; I ſay not by the power of his prerogatiue; but by a due courſe and forme of Law, which no man may repine at: and therefore, if the right may appeare to bee on their ſide, means of recouering that right cannot bee wanting to them. But bee it, that they could ſeeke no higher then the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of the Biſhop; yet is not their caſe ſo deſperate as ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue the ſame to be: For I haue ſhewed before, that not only the high Court of Parliament, but alſo the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Iudges of former times, which many times thwarted with Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in other matters, yet euer aſſiſted them in aſſigning, encreaſing and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the poore <hi>Vicars</hi> portion; yea and preſſed them oft times to this duetie, when they were remiſſe and negligent
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:16794:70"/>
of themſelues: why then ſhould not wee hope the like from the Reuerend Iudges of theſe dayes, whoſe pietie, zeale and feruencie in Religion, is by ſo much greater then was that of their predeceſſors, by how much the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelfe which theſe profeſſe is better, and more worthy of defence and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance then the others was.</p>
            <p>This then is the Maine and capitall point to bee conſidered of, becauſe as a canker it hath moſt ſpread it ſelfe ouer the whole bodie of this kingdom: yet is there one Caſe more, which becauſe it is coſin-german to the other, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Reuerend Biſhops haue right as well as in the other, ought not to bee neglected. And it is the Caſe of thoſe Parſonages which are annexed vnto the Prebends, or dignities of Cathedrall Churches: For theſe, long ſince lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this euill cuſtome of the <hi>Monkes,</hi> to procure the Benefices of other Pariſhes to be annexed vnto them, for the better
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:16794:70"/>
ſupport and maintenance of their ſtate; although <hi>ab initio non fuit ita.</hi> For it is to be noted, That after the time of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the Great, euery greater Citie had a Biſhop reſident therein, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Biſhop a company of learned men alwayes conuerſant about him. Theſe ſerued for Colledges of Reuerend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, to whom al controuerſies of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion were referred, and by whom they were vnder the Biſhop decided: Theſe were called <hi>Presbyteri</hi> which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth as much as <hi>The Elders or Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Church,</hi> by whom the Church was ordered and aduiſed. In which ſence it is that <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logeticon; Nobis praeſident probati quique Seniores: honorem iſtum non pretio ſed te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonio adepti.</hi> Now it is apparant by the Conſtitutions of the Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, reported both in the old <hi>Code,</hi> and alſo in the <hi>Authentiques</hi> of <hi>Iuſtinian;</hi> That theſe were all maintained by Temporall reuenues, which were in
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:16794:71"/>
great abundance caſt vpon them, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the deuotion of the people, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the munificence, and largeſſe of the Emperours; alſo there were <hi>Salaria de publico in diuerſis ſpeciebus Sacro-ſanctis Eccleſijs ministrata,</hi> though afterwards taken from them by <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apostata.</hi> Moreouer, theſe had their ſeuerall hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes wherein they liued with their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and mothers and ſiſters if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. <hi>Illas etiam non relinqui caſtitatis hortatur affectus, quae ante Sacerdotium ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorum legitimum meruere coniugium,</hi> ſaith the Law. And theſe lands the Clergie held free from Taxes and Impoſitions; and not onely they, but alſo their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren held their owne patrimonial lands with like freedome in honour of their fathers Prieſthood. The which I doe the rather alleadge, to let ſome men knowe how farre they are deſtitute of example of former times in their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, while they thinke it a matter vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, That Cathedrall Churches
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:16794:71"/>
ſhould haue any Temporall lands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them, talking of Clergie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as of ſome forraine Nation or Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, which ought not inherite within the land. As for their children they talke of them as of vnlawfull perſons, and ſcantly worth the foſtering, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as yet the law of God maketh their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages as lawfull as ours: and in their children is oftentimes better blood to be found, then in thoſe which ſpeake againſt them. But to returne vnto our purpoſe. Theſe Colledges of learned men in the chiefe Cities of the Empire, were (as I ſaid before) maintained by Temporall reuenues: But not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when theſe means failed them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the peoples indeuotion, or whether through their own ill huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie (for Clergie-mens hands could neuer be tied nor kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliening the reuenues of their Churches) then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan they to caſt abroad their eyes, and to reach out their hands vpon the poore
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:16794:72"/>
Miniſters of the Countrey; who hauing their Tithes, were therewithal content; and in recompence therof held vp pure handes thrice a day vnto their Maker, praying inſtantly for the proſperitie of the people, while they were trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling abroad in their ſeuerall vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This abuſe grew ſo great and ſo hurtfull to the Church, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of <hi>Lateran</hi> thought fit to prouide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; forbidding any Canon of a Church to meddle with a Parſonage of the Countrey.</p>
            <p>Whereupon a certaine <hi>Biſhop</hi> wrote vnto <hi>Honorius</hi> the third Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> complaining, that the <hi>Canons</hi> of his Church, ſince the <hi>Laterane Councill,</hi> were vnable to liue of the reuenues of their <hi>Prebends</hi> (which were, no doubt, that which was left of their Temporall lands) being debarred by the decree of the <hi>Councill</hi> for taking <hi>Parſonages</hi> as they did in former times. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Pope</hi> wrote backe in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:16794:72"/>
               <hi>Si euidens neceſsitas, vel vtilitas exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, Prebendas Ecclefijs tuis pateris de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellis in perpetuum annectendis ijſdem, ficut diſcretione praeuia expedire videris, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentare. Reſeruatâ tamen congruâ Capella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Presbyteris portione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who could haue done this? Who could haue deuiſed ſuch a tricke to elude the letter, and fruſtrate the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a wholeſome law, but he which is the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by a patent of his owne making? The law forbiddeth a <hi>Prebend</hi> to take a <hi>Parſonage</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; becauſe they being two Liuings, and each of them requiring the perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſidence of the partie, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible in one and the ſelfe ſame man. The Pope teacheth them how to auoid this inconuenience, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Canonry</hi> and the <hi>Parſonage</hi> (though neuer ſo farre diſtant in place) to become one Benefice, by vnion: as if the perſonal reſidence, which the Law requireth vpon each of them, were any
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:16794:73"/>
waies procured, or the law fulfilled by this deuice: yet it is ſaid by a certaine <hi>Canoniſt,</hi> that this was <hi>Optimus modus, &amp; Prouiſio augmentandi reditus Canonico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> and I confeſſe as much: But could there haue beene a more Cut-throat courſe deuiſed for the deſtruction of the Pariſh Churches? It is fit there ſhould be ſuch Colledges in <hi>Cathedrall Churches</hi> for the vſes aboue mentioned. True, but let them haue their proper maintenance, as they had in former times out of Temporall lands; not out of Tithes which properly belong to the particular Miniſters of the Pariſh <hi>Churches.</hi> For as <hi>Panormitan</hi> very well ſaith, <hi>Inſtitutio Beneficiorum fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſuſcepit finaliter propter cultum diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Implicantem Diuinorum miniſterium deſeruientium in diuinis eo loco vbi inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Worthy therefore of euerlaſting memory, is the late Action of our <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,</hi> who hauing liberally endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:16794:73"/>
many <hi>Biſhopprickes,</hi> and the ſeuerall dignities and <hi>Prebends</hi> of their <hi>Cathedrall Churches,</hi> with a large and ample pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of lands in the <hi>North</hi> of this kingdome, tooke from them all their <hi>Parſonages</hi> annexed or vnited, and made them <hi>preſentatiue</hi> to the vſe of particular <hi>Incumbents</hi> in time to come, which ſhal thereby be enabled to reſide continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their ſeuerall Pariſhes, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the people.</p>
            <p>But we muſt now take things as they are. <hi>Parſonages</hi> therefore are vnited or annexed to the dignities of <hi>Cathedrall Churches;</hi> yet with a Reſeruation of a conuenient allowance for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar,</hi> as is before declared. There was euer little difference betweene the <hi>Monkes</hi> of <hi>Abbeyes,</hi> and the <hi>Canons</hi> of <hi>Cathedrall Churches:</hi> The difference that was, was this, <hi>quod Canonici regulae inſeruiebant laxiori;</hi> and therefore they are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times paralleled in the law, and what was ordained in the one, was common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:16794:74"/>
               <hi>propter paritatem rationis</hi> extended to the other. They are like in other caſes: they are twinnes in this: yet as the ſtate of things now ſtandeth, the caſe in hand is leſſe doubtfull in theſe <hi>Canons</hi> then in the Succeſſors of the <hi>Monkes;</hi> and the <hi>Biſhops</hi> power in this kind is (if not greater) yet more apparant ouer them, then ouer the other: Becauſe there is no Act of Parlament pretended to defend them from his Iuriſdiction: no Surrender, no Title of the King, no imaginary alteration of their qualitie and nature: but they continue the ſame they were from the beginning. The law then requireth, that euery ſuch <hi>Dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> ſhould haue a perpetuall <hi>Vicar</hi> inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to ſerue in the Church, vnited or annexed to his digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For ſo ſaith the Decretall of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the third. <hi>In ipſâ Eccleſiâ parochiali idoneum &amp; perpetuum hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at vicarium canonicè inſtitutum, qui congruentem habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at de prouentibus ipſius Eccleſiae portionem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:16794:74"/>
And hitherto the Caſe of theſe men is all one with the Caſe of the <hi>Monkes:</hi> but there followeth a <hi>Clauſe</hi> which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Caſe harder with them then with the <hi>Monkes. Alioquin illa ſe ſciat authoritate huius Decreti priuatum, liberè alij conferenda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By occaſion of which wordes the Canoniſts fall into a fell contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues: Whether in default of preſenting a Vicar for Inſtitution, the Prebendarie be <hi>ipſo iure</hi> depriued, and the Parſonage <hi>ipſo facto</hi> made void: Or whether the Parſonage onely bee voidable, and he to be depriued by the ſentence of his Superiour. And the more common receiued opinion is, That it is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> voide: but one of the two is certaine; and which ſoeuer it be, the caſe of the Prebendarie is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then of the Monke: for out of the Monkes Benefice, the Biſhop can onely take a ſufficient maintenance for the Vicar, and muſt leaue the reſt to the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:16794:75"/>
Monke: but to the Canon or Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie he leaueth nothing at all. If there bee any thing left aboue the Vicars maintenance, the Biſhop beſtoweth it in other vſes; and that not onely <hi>pro illa vice,</hi> but alſo ſo often as the Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage ſhall fal voide, during the Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries life, to the ende hee may neuer reape profit thereof, after neglect once committed in this kinde. Againe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Patrons haue ſixe moneths leiſure to preſent: but if the Prebendarie or Canon ſhal not preſent ſo ſoone as with opportunitie he may, the Ordinarie ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his aduantage, and preſenteth as in caſe of lapſe. If afterwards the Canon ſhall come and alledge an impediment, the proofe ſhall alſo lie vpon himſelfe; wherein if he faile, he ſhall neuer be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued. <hi>Poena enim eo ipſo committitur quod facultatem habuit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icarium institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi, &amp; non instituit:</hi> which yet is to be vnderſtood if the neglect be apparant and notorious: Otherwiſe it is fit hee
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:16794:75"/>
ſhould be ſummoned, to ſhew cauſe why not: and if hee appeare not, the Biſhop may informe himſelfe ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and ſo proceede. For it beſeemeth not a reuerend ouerſeer of the Church, to do any thing but with good aduice &amp; deliberation; but aboue all things, he muſt take heede that hee ſeeme not to lie at catch for an aduantage againſt his inferiour fellow Miniſter. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons giuen of the rigour of the Law in this point are, Firſt, becauſe hee deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth no fauour which may be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by another, and yet is negligent in that alſo. And ſecondly, becauſe <hi>Diuine</hi> worſhip is herein tendred; for <hi>Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Clericis conceſſa propter diuinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cultum, eo ipſo definit, quod cultui diuino non incendunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the queſtion may be made: What if the Prebend ſhould preſent a Vicar in due time, but yet ſhall not make him ſuch allowance as the Law requireth? Whether in this caſe the Biſhop may proceede to priuation as in the former;
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:16794:76"/>
or onely proceede by Eccleſiaſticall cenſure, as in the caſe of the Monkes? For mine owne part, I would not at all be an Author, nor willingly a follower of rigorous opinions in the Law. But the wordes are theſe; <hi>Idoneum &amp; perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum habeat Vicarium canonicè inſtitutum, qui (vt praedictum eſt) congruentem habeat de prouentibus Eccleſiae portionem: alioquin illa ſe ſciat auctoritate huius Decreti priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> which clauſe as <hi>Panormitan</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, is referred <hi>ad omne id quod eſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pradictum,</hi> &amp; therefore muſt of neceſsity touch that which ſtands next vnto it.</p>
            <p>Peraduenture ſome man may thinke, that a Vicar is not neceſſarie vpon a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice annexed to a dignitie, if the <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarie</hi> himſelfe will reſide vpon it. But wee muſt remember, that from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning they were not ordeined, but for the cauſe aboue mentioned: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reſide alwayes in the greater Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for the better inſtruction of the people, and daily aſſiſtance of the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:16794:76"/>
in the gouernment of the Church, and therefore in law and reaſon ought to reſide vpon the Prebend in the Citie, and not vpon the Benefice in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. And this is the reſolution of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normitan</hi> vpon this Queſtion. My ſtudie is not at this time to put all the Caſes, and to diſpute all the Queſtions which are made and mooued by the Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Canon Law anent this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: onely I would ſhew, That the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop hath as great a right, and as abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute a power ouer the Cathedrall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as he hath ouer the ſucceſſors of the Monkes: and that therefore hee may and muſt ſee, that their Churches be furniſhed with Perpetuall Vicars, and the Vicars competently and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prouided for by theſe as well as by the other.</p>
            <p>A point of law not to be neglected in this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where there are many Prebendaries which haue no perpetuall Vicars at all vpon their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:16794:77"/>
Benefices: and more, which make their Curats ſo ſmall allowance, as the Monkes, were they liuing, could not in conſcience make them leſſe. I can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for ſome of them, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make them much better, &amp; reſerue any thing for themſelues. But in this caſe the Law is cleere. <hi>Quod primo ſubue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niendum est ſeruitio Eccleſiae, ſecundò indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum neceſsitatibus Canonicorum. Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilius enim eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bowichius, vt Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus egeat qui habet Curam annexam, quàm Vicarius qui illam exercet.</hi> To conclude therfore: if the queſtion be made, <hi>à quo haec congrua portio peti poſsit,</hi> wee may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere as <hi>Petrus Rebuffus</hi> doth, i. <hi>Tam à Patrono exempto quam non exempto, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiastico, vel religioſo, vel ſeculari, ſiue ſint Monachi ſiue Canonici: &amp; ſic etiam à Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo: &amp; generaliter ab ijs qui Eccleſiae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentus recipiunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For all haue robbed, and all muſt make reſtitution. The Vicar or daily Miniſter of the Church muſt haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:16794:77"/>
allowance out of the Tithes of his owne Pariſh, or els God our Father is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured, and our mother the Church wronged. As for thoſe allowances which are now made, as good none at al, as they.</p>
            <p>For the miſchiefe which cometh of theſe ſmall Vicarages and Curateſhips is ſtill the ſame: namely the vnlearnedneſſe of the Miniſterie: for (as <hi>Panormitane</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth) <hi>Ad tenuitatem Beneficiorum neceſſariò ſequitur ignorantia Sacerdotum.</hi> This incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience was long ſince diſcoured: and thence it was that <hi>Alexander</hi> the third bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the horrible couetiſe and abuſe of the <hi>Monkes,</hi> which allowed not aboue the ſixteenth part of the reuenues of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, for the maintenance of the Vicar, addeth this as the curſed fruit of ſo vile a ſtocke, that thence it came to paſſe; <hi>Vt in illis Regionibus penè nullus inueniretur Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos parochialis qui vllam vel modicam habere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peritiam literarum.</hi> And <hi>Clement</hi> the third vpon the ſame occaſion ſaith, That the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt <hi>Monkes,</hi> left ſo ſmall a portion to the Vicars, that they were not able to liue
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:16794:78"/>
thereon, <hi>propter quod ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe contingit, quod non inueniuntur perſonae idoneae, quae huiuſmodi Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias velint recipere; ſicque frequenter minus idoneis conferuntur, ex quo pericula imminent animarum.</hi> The reaſon is plaine, for <hi>Honos alit artes.</hi> We may flatter our ſelues, and ſay, That men ought to take this Calling vpon them, not for any worldly reſpect, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for deuotion vnto God: But experience hath euer proued, that if there be no main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, there will be no Miniſtery. The ſaying of <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> is ſure and true. <hi>Neuer looke for a man</hi> (ſaith <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he) <hi>who to doe you ſeruice will vndoe himſelfe; for you ſhall neuer finde any ſuch.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may not hope that any man will ſet his ſonne to ſchoole, and traine him vp in the ſtudy of Diuinity, vnleſſe there bee hope of wealth and honour in their age. Now from want of learning in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, proceedeth a generall decay of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Whence it was, that (as the learned Chiefe Iuſtice that late was, hath obſerued <note place="margin">Le ſieur Ed. Coke, en Eueſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>incheſters caſe</note> out of the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorie) <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apostata</hi> hauing a purpoſe wholly to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:16794:78"/>
ruine the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, from which himſelf was by tranſgreſſion fallen; vſed not the ſword (as <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and others did) but tooke away the means of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; knowing well that if thoſe once failed, the number of the Preachers would not long continue. And that Prophecie of his wil no doubt one day befulfilled, where he ſaith, That <hi>le decaie des reuenues de ſaint Egliſe, en le fine ſera ſubuerſion del ſeruice de Dieu, &amp; de ſon Religion. i.</hi> That the decay of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of holy Church, will one day be the ſubuerſion of the ſeruice of God, &amp; of his Religion. For <hi>Plowden</hi> in his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries ſheweth, That the reuerend Iudges of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> long ſince obſerued, that by the abuſe of the <hi>Monkes,</hi> in applying all to their own bellies, and leauing nothing to the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, which yet (as hee ſaith) were deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ordained of purpoſe, to ſupply the defects of the <hi>Monkes,</hi> and others in the miniſtery &amp; ſeruice of the Church, there crept in many abuſes: and hee addeth, that, <hi>As the reuenew of the Pariſh Church decaied, ſo likewiſe did Preaching.</hi> And
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:16794:79"/>
this was the cauſe why the Emperor <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> was ſo carefull, that the number of his Clergie ſhould not exceed the proportion of meanes which was laid out for their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment. For the end he ſaw would be the beggery of the Miniſtery, whence could not chooſe but follow the ruine of that holy Order, and conſequently, a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall decay of true Religion. We neede not paſſe the Seas to ſeeke for proofe of this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion. What is ſo poore as our Clergie here in <hi>Ireland?</hi> I ſpeake not of our Prelats, God increaſe it to them, and make it ten times more then now it is: But what is ſo deformed a ſight as the face of our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, which conſiſteth of Curats and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, is? But withall, what can be more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned then they are? and what can be more irreligious, or leſſe vnderſtanding of what belongeth to God and godlines then the people is? which could not be, if there were men among them to teach and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them: For the people is as capable of inſtruction as any other: and where they come to be informed of the truth, are
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:16794:79"/>
as zealous thereof, as any Nation in the world. This miſchiefe is great, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury and iniuſtice whence it proceedeth, is no leſſe. For wherefore are Tithes giuen, but in conſideration and recompence of preaching the word, and miniſtring the <hi>Sacraments</hi> to thoſe which giue them? <hi>Is it a great thing</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) if when wee ſowe ſpirituall things, wee reape carnall things?</hi> Preaching therefore, and other diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, is the thing in lieu whereof the Tithes are payd vnto the Miniſter. And our <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi> affirme, that <hi>Beneficium non debetur niſi propter officium.</hi> What Iuſtice therefore, that a man ſhould part with a <hi>Tenth</hi> of all that God hath giuen him, in bargaine to haue the word of God truely preached to him, and yet be defrauded of that alſo? And the worſe is, that the greater the Pariſh was, and the greater the charge which it was at, in this regard, the worſe were they ſerued, and the leſſe reſpect was euer had vnto them: for euen as heretofore, the whiter the <hi>Cow,</hi> the ſooner ſhe came vnto the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar; ſo the fairer the Benefice, the more in
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:16794:80"/>
danger was it euer of <hi>Appropriation.</hi> And as in the ſacke of a citie, the faireſt of euery kind is ſooneſt made a ſpoile vnto the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier: ſo in that <hi>Inuaſion</hi> which the <hi>Regular Clergie</hi> made vpon the <hi>Churches,</hi> the greateſt and richeſt <hi>Benefices</hi> were the firſt made a pray vnto the <hi>Monkes:</hi> and the poore Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners, in ſtead of a man of learning and wiſedome, by whom they might be taught &amp; aduiſed in things belonging to this life, and the life to come; were turned ouer to bee ſerued by them, which were ſcarce worthy to ſerue horſes. This ſaddle was put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the peoples backs by perſwading them that the Pope was CHRISTS Vicar here on earth, and by vertue of that office, had power in himſelfe to diſpoſe of all things belonging to the Church. The <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> goe further, and teach, that he is Lord and maſter of all together. But the <hi>Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> aſwell in their late action a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as heretofore in the yere 1429 in the caſe of <hi>Iohn Sarrazin</hi> a Friar predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant; and at ſundry other times haue op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed themſelues againſt this vnbridled
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:16794:80"/>
and vnlimited power of the Popes. And the Churches of <hi>France</hi> by their example animate their Kings and Courts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to doe the like; &amp; to withſtand their vſurpation, which neuer tended but to the eſtabliſhing of a Monarchie in that See, with the ruine of other Churches.</p>
            <p>The ends which the <hi>Popes</hi> pretended in theſe Appropriations, were, Increaſe of Religion, and Hoſpitalitie: what good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath reaped by them hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed: and as for Hoſpitalitie, <hi>Plowden</hi> ſaith, That Impropriations were the decay thereof, eſpecially in thoſe places where it ought principally to haue beene kept, that is, in the Pariſhes themſelues. Had we liued in thoſe daies, no doubt we would not haue done as our Predeceſſors did: but hereby are we witneſſes againſt our ſelues, that we are the Succeſſours of them which did ſuch things: we haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede diuided the ſinne with them: they were the robbers, and we are the receiuers: they tooke from the Church, and wee enioy it, And I woonder, that following
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:16794:81"/>
their example, we doe not feare their end.</p>
            <p>To conclude: If this courſe be legall, and may be taken for the better mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the poore Clergie in this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble kingdome, well and good. If not: God grant ſome other may; for if none be, fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well Religion: and what can then enſue but the abomination of deſolation in the higheſt places of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Which GOD forbid.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON Printed by IOHN BILL. ANNO DOM. M. DC. XX.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16794:81"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
